<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The state of the godly both in this life, and in the life to come deliuered in a sermon at Chudleigh in Devon: at the funeralls of the right worshipfull, the Ladie Elizabeth Courtney, the 11. of Nouember, 1605. And published for the instruction, and consolation of the faithfull. By R.W. minister. Whereunto is annexed the christian life and godly death of the sayd worshipfull Lady Elizabeth Courtney.</title>
            <author>Wolcomb, Robert, b. 1567 or 8.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15674</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106614</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842327</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842327</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6972</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15674)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6972)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 583:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The state of the godly both in this life, and in the life to come deliuered in a sermon at Chudleigh in Devon: at the funeralls of the right worshipfull, the Ladie Elizabeth Courtney, the 11. of Nouember, 1605. And published for the instruction, and consolation of the faithfull. By R.W. minister. Whereunto is annexed the christian life and godly death of the sayd worshipfull Lady Elizabeth Courtney.</title>
                  <author>Wolcomb, Robert, b. 1567 or 8.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 73, 73-83, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Bradock] for Roger Iackson, and are to be sold at his shoppe neere the Conduit in Fleetstreete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.W. = Robert Wolcomb, who has signed the dedication.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Courtney, Elizabeth, --  Lady, d. 1605 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6972:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6972:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> STATE OF THE godly both in this life, and <hi>in the life to come:</hi> Deliuered in a Sermon at Chud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leigh in Devon: at the funeralls of the right Worſhipfull, the Ladie <hi>Elizabeth Courtney, the</hi> 11. of Nouember, 1605.</p>
            <p>And publiſhed for the inſtruction, and conſolation of the faithfull.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. W.</hi> Miniſter.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed the chriſtian life and godly death of the ſayd worſhipfull Lady <hi>Elizabeth Courtney.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal: 112.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He hath diſtributed and giuen to the poore, his righteouſnes remaineth for euer.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>At London</hi> Printed for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhoppe neere the Conduit in Fleetſtreete. 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6972:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6972:2"/>
            <head>To the worſhipfull, his good <hi>friend,</hi> Thomas Clifford, <hi>Eſquire, grace, mercy &amp; peace from god</hi> the father, and from Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</hi> you ſee the effect of importunity, and the efficacy of your fauor towards me; in that the ſermon which was at firſt priuate, in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the Audients; is now become publique in peſpect of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Wherein it reſembleth the Image, that is taken out of the painters ſhop, where few behold it, and placed in the open market, where euery one will cenſure it. I haue deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neated two dwelling places of the godly, as my memory, notes and parentheſis of vacant
<pb facs="tcp:6972:3"/> time permitted: thone fading, reſtles, and wretched in earth, thother permane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, quiet, and bleſſed in heauen. And I wiſh that my labour therin, may be like the liuelyeſt pict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure and poeme, which the more neerly, nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly, and often it is ſuruiewed, the more it feeds the eye and the mind of the behoulder with delectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as the iudicious, or rather ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſorious Poet ſays, both of the one &amp; thother
<q>
                  <l>Vt pictura, poeſis, erit quae, ſi propiùs ſtes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Horat. in Arte.</note>Te capiet magis, &amp; quaeda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſi longiùs abſtes.</l>
                  <l>Haec amat obſcuru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, volet haec ſubluce videri</l>
                  <l>Haec placuit ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>el, haec decies repetita placebit</l>
               </q> Neither can J conceale, that in diuulgating of this ſermon, I was both vnwilling, &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: vnwilling, becauſe of the ſlenderneſſe thereof, and the captiouſnes of theſe critick times: in which that is vſuall which <hi>Salust</hi> ſaid to <hi>Caeſar;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sal. ad Caeſar. de ordinand. rep.</note> 
               <hi>(ad repraehenda aliena facta, aut dicta, ardet omnibus animus)</hi> all are ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly bent to reproue other mens dooings, or ſayings: willing, becauſe I deſired to deci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pher the ſincerity of myne obſequiouſneſſe towards her, whoſe memory <hi>I</hi> wold my te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity &amp; obſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy were able to eternize: &amp; becauſe <hi>I</hi> was loath to reiecte your preſſing motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> curteſies may
<pb facs="tcp:6972:3"/> duly craue the vtmoſt of my poſſibility. Her perſpicuous worthines, your experimented kindnes, mine own prope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to endeuor to do good by any means, haue more ſwaied with me, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I could be hindred to edify the faithfull, and induced to withhold good fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the owners thereof, by ſurmizing, that the froward will condemne me, either of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency or flattery. From flattery the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall acclamation of multitudes, that both knew her, and heard of her, will, (I know) acquit me; from the blame of voluntary &amp; ſhameleſſe intruding my ſelfe into the ſight of the world, your learned apology (I hope) ſhall purge me. For malice had wanted one morſell to thruſt into her inſaturable gorge, had not your forcible perſwaſions ſubdew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, and caſt me as a pray vnto her deuou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring teeth. Neuertheleſſe, let one tax the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lixity, not weighing the extraordinary occur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rents: let another balance in the weights of worldly eloquence, the cours &amp; vnpoliſhed ſtyle; deſiring perhaps finer breade then is made of wheate, and rather an eloquent, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> learned Phyſitian to cure his maladie: let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother reprooue thinculcating of vulgar ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations, and obuious documents: forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, aſwell that Paul, that noble inſtructor
<pb facs="tcp:6972:4"/> of the gentiles, (by daily reading of whoſe Epiſtles, the golden mouthed father ſaide, that he knew how to deuide the word of truth aright) was not aſhamed, to write the ſame things again; as alſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t becometh rather an <hi>Athenian,</hi> than a chriſtian, to hant after nouelties: yet they that haue their wits exerciſed, to diſcerne good from euill, ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l perceiue, that J haue not erred from the faith; and that J haue not depraued the <hi>depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum,</hi> and talent of wholeſom doctrin, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the church by Chriſt, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by the apoſtle to his ſcholler Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim. 6.20,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>incent Liri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. adu. propha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uat. cap. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> J haue kept (to borow the words of mel lifluous <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis,</hi> on the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde exhortation of the apoſtle) that was committed vnto me, not that I haue inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; that J receiued, not that I deuiſed: that I learned, not that J forged of mine owne wit; that hath beene publickly taughte, not priuately maintained. As I haue receiued gold, ſo J haue endeuoured to render and returne gold: and not to giue, either impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, lead, or fraudulently, copper, and the ſhew of gold, in ſteed of ſincere gold. And in returning it, J haue been, <hi>(non author, ſed cuſtos, non inſtitutor, ſed ſectator, non ducens,
<pb facs="tcp:6972:4"/> ſed ſequens: &amp; cum dixerim noue, non dixi no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua:)</hi> not an author, but a keeper: not a tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, but a ſcholler, not a leader, but a follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: and albeit J haue arraied ſomethings in attire of a new faſhion, yet there is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the matter and ſubſtance. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not diſtruſting, but that as I haue put this ſermon in writing at your entreaty, the conciſe ſinewes and epitome whereof was els likely to haue been vtterly motheaten; ſo you will patronize it againſt ſuch malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes, as either reprehend, that they will not amend, or elſe are deſpiſers of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their ſelues were not agents: with my praier, that it may benefite as many, as did beare vndiſſembled loue vnto her, whoſe happy remembraunce hath both wrung it out of my hands, and drawn it into the light and that the faith which I am perſwaded is in you, may dwell in you vnto the end, as it firſt dwelt in your worthy grandmother, and in your godly mother, I commit you and yours to the gratious protection of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, whom I deſire to ſanctifie vs throgh out, and to keep our whole ſpirit, and ſoule, and body, blameles, vnto the comming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord <hi>Rob. VVolcomb.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="Scripture">
            <pb facs="tcp:6972:5"/>
            <head>Reuelat. Chap. 7. v. 13.14.15.16.17.</head>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13.</hi> And one of the Elders ſpake, ſaying vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me, what are theſe which are araied in long white robes, &amp; whence came they?</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14.</hi> And I ſaid to him, lord thou knoweſt: and he ſayd to me; Theſe are they which came out of great tribulation, and haue waſhed their long robes, and haue made their long robes white in the blood of the Lambe.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15.</hi> Therefore are they in the preſence of the throne of God, and ſerue him day &amp; night in his temple: and he that ſitteth on the throne will dwell among them.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16.</hi> They ſhall hunger no more, neither thirſt any more, neither ſhall the Sunne light on them, neither any heate.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17.</hi> For the Lambe, who is in the midſt of the throne, ſhall gouern them: and ſhall lead them to the liuely fountains of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eys.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6972:5"/>
            <head>The ſtate of the godly in this life, and <hi>in the life to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch and ſo greate is the loue of god towards his choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people, that he doth not only giue them war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of dangers enſuing, but doth oftentimes deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them from manifold calamities, wher with others are ouerwhelmed.<note place="margin">Gen. chap. 6.7.8. Gen. 19.</note> So <hi>Noah</hi> had warning of the coming of the flood, &amp; was deliuered from the violence thereof. So <hi>Lot</hi> had warning of the deſtruction of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and eſcaped the fury of the fire and brimſtone. So the Iſraelits had war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the killing of al the firſt born amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the <hi>Egiptians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exodus 12.</note> &amp; by the blood of the paſchal lamb wer preſerued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſtroier. So againe the Iſraelites paſſed through the red ſea,<note place="margin">Exodu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 14.</note> as through dry grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6972:6"/> but the waters cloſed on their enimies the <hi>Egiptia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi> So before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> captiuity, the Iews y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mourned &amp; ſighed for the abominations which were committed in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 9.</note> had a marke ſet on theyr foreheades, and were exempted from the deſolation; and other which had not the marke, were not ſpared, but ſmitten without pitty. And as the lord in the ſeuen trumpets had proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded diuerſe miſeries to be inflicted vppon men of all ſorts,<note place="margin">cap. 8. 7. &amp;c.</note> ſo in this chapter there is a caution and prouiſo for the godly: for before the fowr angels by holding the 4. winds do hurt the earth, with haile and fire, or that a burning mountaine kill the creatures of the ſea; or the fallen ſtarre turneth the liuing waters into mortall wormewood, or the ſonne and moone bee ſmitten till the ſeruants of God were ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in their foreheads: <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the viſion of thoſe which were numbred and ſealed: Iewes, of all the tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and forty and fowr thouſand: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a numberles number of the gentiles, of all nations,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Mare. 13.51.</note> and kindreds, and people, and tongues; who ſtoode before the throne of god, to worſhippe him and prayſe him,
<pb facs="tcp:6972:6"/> and were clothed in long white robes, that is, were couered with the vnſpotted righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of Chriſt, and had palms in their hands, in token of the victory obtained by Chriſt, againſt the fleſh, the world, and Satan. After this <hi>Iohn</hi> heard the congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation and thankſgiuing of thoſe which were ſealed, for that they were ſaued and preſerued: for they cried with a loud voice ſaying, <hi>Saluation commeth from our God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 10.12.</note> 
               <hi>that ſitteth vpon the throne, and from the Lamb.</hi> Vnto which crye all the angells applaude, and worſhip God, ſaying, Amen. <hi>Praiſe, and glory, and wiſedome, and thanks, and honor, and power, and might, be vnto our god for euermore. Amen.</hi> Now theſe words which I haue read, containe the expounding of the viſion that <hi>Iohn</hi> ſawe.<note place="margin">Iunius in Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>calypſ.</note> In which expoſition, three things are to be noted. 1 The queſtion of the Elder, to ſtir vp <hi>Iohn</hi> to deeper conſideration, in the 13 verſe. 2 <hi>Iohns</hi> anſwer to the Elder, in the firſt part of the 14. verſe. 3 The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of the Elder, in the reſt of the 14 verſe and vnto the end of the 17 verſe. In which reply the Elder declares, thoſe which were numbred and ſealed to be the ſaints,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6972:7"/> whom he deſcribes, firſt by their acts, that is their ſuffrings, and work of faith in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt donne in the former perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to be continued in the future ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, in the 14 verſe. Secondly by their glory both preſent in the 15 v. and to come: partly in their ful deliuerance from all calamities and annoyances, in the 16. verſe, and partly in participation and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of all good things, which the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of woonted myſeries ſhall neuer aboliſh or diminiſhe: in the 17. v. <hi>And this is begun in this life, but accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed afterwards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that the Elder doth aſke a queſtion of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nterpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the text.</note> whether he knew, who thoſe were, which were arrayed in long white robes, and whence they came: he behaueth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like a diligent teacher, who being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to enſtruct his ſcholler in that hee knows not, he preuenteth him, by enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, whither he know it, or not. Whereby the Elder ſignifieth, how prompt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy they that are led by the ſpirite of God, and are endued with knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, ſhould bee to informe the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant. And in that <hi>John</hi> yeelds a modeſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6972:7"/> aunſwer to the Elder, acknowledging his ignorance; by attributing knowledge to the Elder: for in that he ſayth <hi>Lord thou knowſt;</hi> he ſayth thus, Lord I knowe not: Lord thou knowſt; lord teache me: he doth aduertize vs, to be wiſe with ſobriety; and not to bee puffed vp with an ouerweening opinion of our learning, but to recken it no ſhame and diſparagement, to be taught the certaynty of thoſe good thinges which we neuer learned,<note place="margin">Marlor: &amp; Sebaſt, Meyer in Apocal.</note> Whereas the Saints are ſayed to come out of great tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, although the Elder ſpake this, chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye touching the former perſecutions by the heathen Empires, and may alſo bee vnderſtoode of the perſecution which An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſhoulde raiſe againſt the Church: yet generally it may be vnderſtood, of the vniuerſall troubles and afflictions of this life, in that all the children of God, come from greate affliction vnto greate reſte, from myſery vnto glory, from priſon vnto a kingdom: from thraldom vnto freedom: from death vnto life. The long robes of the ſaints which were waſhed, is the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, righteouſneſſe, and innocency of Chriſt, wherewith the godly being cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6972:8"/> they do walke boldly, and are found iuſt and vnblameable before the Lord. And the making white of the long robes in the Lambs hlood, is when the godly do walk in the fayth of chriſt, and do ſuffer the cros patiently after his example.</p>
            <p>But howe can blood make white? The faithfull are waſhed white with the Lambes bloude, in that they are purged in conſcience from deade workes to ſerue the liuing GOD,<note place="margin">Hebr. 9 13. Reuel. 1.5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. 1.19.</note> by the blood of CHRISTE, who tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the eternall ſpirite offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto god, an vnſpotted ſacrifice. And here falls to ground the Romiſh doctrine of indulgences,<note place="margin">Acts 10.3. 1 Iohn. 1.7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 5.21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 1.15. Acts 20.28. Hebr 10 14.</note> and diſpenſation of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perabounding merits of Saints, for if the faithfull are ſufficiently purged and clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the blood of the lamb, where is the treaſure of ſupererogation of Saintes? Where it is ſayd, that the godly are in the preſence of the throne of god this may be taken, not only for that bleſſed and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et worſhip, which the godly departed out of the body, yeeld to the lorde in heauen, without externall and laborſome ſeruice: but alſo for their worſhipping of God,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6972:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> while they liue in this mortall body: and while they in this life are ſo deuoted to the ſeruing of god,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2:6. Col. 3:1. 2. Cor: 3:6.</note> and do ſo frame theyr whole life after his will, and do ſo ſeeke to glorifie god, and to edify their neighbor, as if they were already placed in gods he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly temple, before the throne of God, and before his holy Angells. As for this, that the godly ſerue god day and night in his temple:<note place="margin">Pſal. 134.1. Leuit, 8.35. Luke 18:1. 1 Theſſ. 5.17. Luke 2.37. Pſalm 1:2: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Leu. 26:12: 2 Cor: 6:16: Reu: 3:20 1 Iohn 1:3: Gen. 17.1:</note> the Angell alludes to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the ould Leuites, for otherwiſe ther is no night in heauen: or els by ſeruing god day and night, may be meant, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall endeuouring of the godly to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie god, euen in all their actions. And that god will dwell among them, or vpon them, what doth it ſignify els, but that as they are gods people, ſo he will be theyr God: and as they will paſſe their life in feare and reuerence, as being alway in the ſight of god, ſo god will haue familiar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation among them, and wilbe theyr protector and exceeding greate rewarde. To hunger and thirſt no more; is to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied with all good and deſirable things: for meate and drinke are the chiefeſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the deſires and cares of this life:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6972:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> and to eate and drinke,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.35: Luke 22.29: Eſai. 65.13: Ezech. 34.13:</note> is in ſcripture, to lead an happy and pleaſant life. By the ſunne and heate, that after this life ſhall fall no more vpon the godly, muſt bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the end and ceaſing of the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wherewith the faithfull are exerciſed in this life. For as in hoate regions, the parching heate of the ſunne dooth much grieue the inhabitants: and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re god ſhadowed his people by day with a pillar of a cloude,<note place="margin">Exod. 13.11:</note> from the feruente heate of the ſunne: ſo the ſcorching of affliction dooth annoy and moleſt the godlye, as long as they remaine in this world: but after the race of mortality is finiſhed, the place of tribulation ſhalbe found no more. And here euen the leaſt droppe of conſolation, that flowes from this one place of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is enough to quenche the whole fire &amp; flame of <hi>Purgatory.</hi> For how may pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory ſtand, if the faithfull after this life ſhall no more be accumbred with Sunne, or any heate? Who is the Lambe in the mids of the throne; but Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>The Lamb of god that taketh away the ſinn of the world?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn. 1.36:</note> and who is the great ſhepheard and Biſhop of ſoules,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that doth feede and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6972:9"/> gouern the godly like ſheepe, but Chriſt? and what is the leading of the faithfull to the liuing waters;<note place="margin">Ezech 34.3 Iohn. 10.14 Acts 20.28. Pſalm 23.1: Iohn 4.10: &amp; 7, 28. Iſai. 55, 1. Ezech 36.26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> but that they after this life ſhall liue ioyfully, and bleſſedly, being freed from all calamities? and what is it to wipe away all teares from the godlye; but that the fulnes of ioyes ſhall ſwalow vp all ſorow and cauſe of ſadnes? For as the ioy of the wicked is turned into ſorow ſo the ſorrowe of the godly is turned into comfort. And the <hi>Angell</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Iames 4.9. Iſai 65.18: Mat. 5.4 Iohn 16 20.</note> that <hi>euerye teare ſhall be wipt away:</hi> to giue vs to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that the teares of the electe are diuers, as their tribulations are diuers. One laments becauſe he hath done euill; another laments becauſe he hath not done good: one lamentes, becauſe he beares the hard rod of affliction, another lamentes becauſe he is aſſaulted by vices: one la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments becauſe he is abſent and a ſtranger from the kingdom of heauen: &amp; for that the blindnes of worldlings is greate: another laments, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gods word is contemned &amp; deſpiſed: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord wil end all tears, &amp; wil refreſh his people w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eternal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And here is ouerturned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erroneous doctrin of mans merit; for the onely efficient cauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6972:10"/> of the glory of the elect, both heere and hereafter, is but one, namely the lamb, the Meſſias, the mediator, and ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Although many things offer themſelues in this text to our view, and are worthy of due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templation, yet I haue ſelected only two which at this time ſhal be vnfolded, and made manyfeſt vnto you, as meeteſt for this preſent occaſion &amp; aſſembly; The firſt is the ſtate and condition of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in this life. The ſecond is the ſtate &amp; condition of the faithfull after this life. For the firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſtate of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odly in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe <hi>v, 14, 16, 17</hi>
               </note> to wit the ſtate and condition of the godly in this life, in that it is heere ſayde, that they came out of greate tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, that they ſhall after this life hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger no more, neither thirſt any more, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſun ſhal not light on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither any heate and that God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eies; this ſhewes, that while the godly are abiding in this life, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure tribulation, they hunger, and thirſt they are annoyed with ſun and heate, and they liue in the valley of miſery, which compelleth to ſhed teares. And it can be no other wiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, For our Lord &amp; maſter
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6972:10"/> Chriſt ſayeth, that if any will come after him, &amp; be his diſciple, he muſt deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf &amp; take vp his cros dayly &amp; follow him If we will be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ſcollars of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luke 9, 23.</note> it is not enough, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fes or profes him to ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>due &amp; curbe the vitious affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of our na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tural inclination, but we muſt vndergoe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cros, &amp; tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither is yt enough, once or twiſe to vndergoe it, but take vp our croſſe dayly. For as one day followeth another, ſo there is a ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; plurality of tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> purſue the godly. If wee purpoſe to build the tower of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>anity we muſt firſt caſt on theſe coſts,<note place="margin">Luke: 14, 28<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> &amp; if we wil fight battails of vnfained profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we muſt make redy to encounter diuers &amp; dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerus aduerſaries. And therfore <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> knowing, that affliction is a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnſeparable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion of godlines, did not only publiſh the truth at <hi>Liſtra, Iconium, &amp; Antiochia</hi> but confirmed the diſciples harts, &amp; exhorted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in the faith and not to fall away and bee daunted through tribulations, affirming, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt through many afflictions enter into the kingdome of God. This generall lot of the godly <hi>Paule</hi> moſte expreſſely declares inferring vpon his own preſident,<note place="margin">2, Tim, 3, 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>That all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6972:11"/> that will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tim 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>ſhal ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer perſecution. <hi rend="sup">d</hi>
               </hi> For whome he loueth, he chaſteneth, and he ſcourgeth euery ſon that he receiuerh. If we endure chaſtning God offereth himſelfe vnto vs, as vnto ſonnes? for what ſonne is it, whome the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther chaſtneth not; And therfore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle is bould to conclude,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebr 12 8.</note> that <hi>if wee bee without correction, whereof all are parta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers, then are we baſtards, and not ſonnes.</hi> Be hold Noah: behold Lott: behold A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Izaac &amp; Iaakob: behold Ioſeph behold Moſes: were not all theſe the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ſonnes of God? and yet were not al theſe preſſed with tribulations? The time will bee to ſhorte to ſpeake of <hi>Iob,</hi> of <hi>Dauid;</hi> of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> who where the true and deare ſeruants of God: and yet were tried in the fornace of affliction. Chriſt himſelfe was aſſaulted of Sathan, had trappes layed in his waye by his enemies, was hated of ſinfull men, and did flee from their fury, felt hunger, &amp; weriſomnes of body: was mocked, &amp; ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; railed vpon, &amp; deſpitefully entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; ſpit vpon, and crowned with thorns, &amp; beaten with whips, and at laſt led to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6972:11"/> croſſe, and to execution, tyll hee dyed, and gaue vp the ghoſt: ſo that the onely example of CHRIST himſelfe, whoſe whole life was nothing but a paſſion and tribulation, may ſuffice to teache vs, <hi>That the diſciple is not aboue his Maſter, nor the ſeruante aboue his Lord:</hi> It is enough <hi>for the diſciple to bee as his Maſter, and the ſeruant as his Lorde, If they haue called the Maſter of the howſe Beelzebub,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth, 10.2</note> 
               <hi>how much more them of his houſehould? <hi rend="sup">f.</hi>
               </hi> For if we ſuppoſe: that we ſhall feele no tribulations, we muſt not i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magin, that we can be true Chriſtians Aſſoon as we begin to liue godly in chriſt (ſayth ſaint Auguſtine,<note place="margin">Cum c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> piè in Chriſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> viuere, ingre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es torcular, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parate ad pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuram. Aug: Pſal. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note>) we enter into the winepreſſe, and we ought to prepare our ſelues for wringing and preſſing, and we muſt take heede that we bee not found ſo drye grapes, that we yeeld out noe good licour when we are preſſed.</p>
            <p>An heathen Philoſopher cold ſay, that the man is moſt vnhapy, vnto whom no aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſity betideth; it is an argument, that he is contemned of god, as a weake &amp; ſluggiſh perſon. A ſword-player acounts it reproch to fight with a man of no valour: for hee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6972:12"/> knowes that there is noe glory to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhe him that is vanquiſhed without dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. Euen ſo worketh gods prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce He ſetteth vpon euery one endued with moſt courage,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ihil eo infoeli <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, cui nihil e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enit aduerſi: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgumentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deo illum con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mni, vt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ellem &amp; ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. in lib. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouid Dei.</note> &amp; trieth his power againſt him. He tried by the fier <hi>Mutius,</hi> by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty <hi>Fabritius,</hi> by baniſhment <hi>Rutilius,</hi> by torments <hi>Regulus,</hi> by poyſon <hi>Socrates,</hi> by death <hi>Cato,</hi> Thus ſayd an Ethnick of thoſe that ſought but glory among men &amp; had but vain glory for their reward, but how much more truly may it be ſayd, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god tryed <hi>Iob</hi> by botches, &amp; <hi>Tobit</hi> by blindnes and <hi>Stephen</hi> by ſtones, &amp; the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> by bands and priſonment, and the martyrs by infinit tortures? For whoſoeuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to retourne into Paradiſe: muſt paſſe through the fire and water of affliction; whether it be Peter the Apoſtle, to whom the keys of the Kingdome of heauen were giuen;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mnes qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Paradiſum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dire defide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, oportet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſire per ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em et a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e fuerit Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us &amp;c. Aug. ſermone ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppium.</note> or whether it be Paule the Lords choſen veſſell or whether it be <hi>Iohn,</hi> to whome heauenly miſteries were reuealed They muſt needs all ſay, that without tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation and affliction, we cannot come to God,</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:6972:12"/>
            <p>Neyther doe the faithfull alone ſuffer tribulation in this life, but miſery &amp; afflic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion is commonly incident to all man kind as holy Iob ſayth, man that is born of a woman, is of ſhorte continuance: and full of trouble.<hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">i</hi>
               </hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayeth not,<note place="margin">Iob. 14.1.</note> that man and this man are battered with trouble: but he vſeth the indefinite word (man) that euery one might remember his own lot. So that the ſonne of <hi>Sirach</hi> ſeemes to comment on Iob when he writes, that great trauell is created for all men, and an heauy yoke vpon the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> from the day that they goe out of their mothers wombe, till the day that they retourn to the mother of all thinges. Thoughts and feare of the hearte, and i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of things waited for, wrath &amp; enuy troble and vnquietnes, rigor &amp; ſtrife, fear of death, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day and death: theſe are vſuall, from him that ſitteth vppon the glorious throne, vnto him that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath in the earth &amp; aſhes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thed in blew ſilke and weareth a crowne euen vnto him that is cloathed in ſimple linne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note n="k" place="margin">Ecclus 40.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2.3.4.5.</note> Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s life is like a rock in the Sea, beaten vppon of the floods on euery ſide: &amp; like a tree on an high and open
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6972:13"/> hill, blowne on by the winds, from euery quarter: and like a burning candle, which may be put out, by ſundry meanes, but if yt be not putt out, yet in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance it burnes out it ſelfe: and like a butt or marke vnto which ſorrow ſhootes, and danger ſhootes, and miſaduenture ſhootes and at laſt death, that moſt ſure archer ſhootes, and ſtrikes it dead. What our ſubſtance is, namely duſt and earth, and what our eſtate is, namely painefull, labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and comberſome, is euident, by that ſpeach of god to Adam after his fall <hi>in the ſweate of thy face</hi> (ſaith god] <hi>ſhalt thou eat bread, til thou retourn to the earth: for out of it waſt thou taken, becaus thou art duſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.19</note> 
               <hi>and to duſt ſhalt thou retourne.</hi> And therfore the Pſalmiſt affirms our brittle ſubſtance and our wreched life, to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, whie God hath compaſſion on them that feare him, as a father hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on his children. For (ſaith he) he knoweth whereof wee are made, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth that wee are but duſt.<note place="margin">Pſa. 103.13.14 1 Chro. 29.15.</note> This ſweete ſinger of Iſraell calles himſelfe and euery man beſides, but a ſtranger and ſo iourner, like as all our fathers were,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6972:13"/> A ſtraunger and traueller hath litle or no contentation, til he come to the end of his iourney, either he complaines of the raine, or of the wind, or of the heate of the ſunne, or of his lodging, or of his vnfitting dyet, or of the yrkſomnes of his iourney: ſo man hath ſtill occaſion to complain of his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in this life, and can neuer enioy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſecurity, while hee remayneth heere. And vpon good reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet breake foorth, and ſay, <hi>Lord what is man, that thou regardeſt him, or the ſonne of man, that thou thinkeſt vppon him?</hi> Hee ſtayes not heere, but declares the cauſe of his admiration: man (ſayeth hee) <hi>is like to vanitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 144:3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>his dayes are like a ſhaddowe that vaniſheth.</hi> As if he had ſayde, though wee feed our body neuer ſo deliciouſly, though we cloath our fleſh neuer ſo ſumptuouſly, though we prouide for our life neuer ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſlye, yet our dayes tary not, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte as vanitye. Thou that floweſt with wealthe, and glorieſt in reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; wilte thou knowe thy weight? thou art ligher then vanity, then nothing: wilt thou know the length of thy dayes? they are a ſpanne: wilt thou know how, and in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6972:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> what ſorte thou fadeſt? as a ſlender pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and image. For when Dauid had de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſired the lord that he might know his end &amp; the meaſure of his dayes, what it was and how long he had to lyue: he preſently giues himſelfe this anſwere <hi>beholde, thou haſt made my dayes as an handbredth and my age is as nothing in reſpect of thee ſurely euery man in his beſt ſtate is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vanity: doubtles man walketh in a ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dow.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.4.5.</note> And what confidence ſhould we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in this fickle life, ſins the oracle and voice of God commaunded <hi>Iſayah</hi> to crye that <hi>all fleſh is graſſe, &amp; all the grace therof is as as the flower of the field: the graſſe withreth the flower fadeth, becauſe the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the lord bloweth vpon it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 4.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſurely the people is graſſe;</hi> One herbe may be ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then another, one herb may be of more virtue then another, one flower maye bee of more endurance then another yet at laſt all hearbes wither, and all flowers fade ſo one man maye bee wiſer then an other; and richer then an other and learnedder then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and honorabler then another and ſtronger then an other: But the ſtate
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6972:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> and condition of all fleſh is, to be miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and mortall. <hi>For what is our life?</hi> (ſayth bleſſed <hi>Iames:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2, Iam. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>Jt is euen a vapour that api<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peareth for a little time, and afterward vani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſheth awaye.</hi> Doeſt thou not marke, how hugie and and ſtatelie the vapors ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peare, when they mount vpward vnto the heauen, and yet how ſoone they vaniſh: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the turning of the hande? Another ſuch thing is this life, though it decke it ſelfe with neuer ſo glorious pompe, yet it falls awaie as a bubble: to day a man, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrowe none. <hi>Gregorie Nazianzene</hi> tompares our life to a toppe which chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whirl, &amp; driue to &amp; froe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcourge,
<q>
                  <l>Surſum deorſum, voluitur, reuoluitur,</l>
                  <l>Et cum videtur ſtare, conſiſtit minus:</l>
               </q> It is toſſed vp and down, foorth and back and when it ſeems to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly,<note place="margin">or to mooue leaſt it whir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth moſt. Nazia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. carm ex tranſlatione bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>llij. <hi>Gen. 11.2. Dan. 4.27.</hi>
               </note> it falls ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly. And therfor (if any wil follow his counſel) he may in three wordes deſcribe fullie the life of man,
<q>Inſomnium, fumuſue, floſue herbae breuis:</q> It is a dream, a vapor, a flower. If any ſhold be ſo vainglorius &amp; ambitious, as to build the tower of <hi>Babel</hi> with <hi>Nimrod</hi> or a magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pallace with <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:6972:15"/> or a piller to preſerue a memorable fame with <hi>Abſalom:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 18.28.</note> yet the hungry teeth of time and continuance wold deuour the moſt ſpecious workes, and will eyther conſume them before vs, or vs before them If faith could ſaue from death, <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould not haue dyed, if might could do it <hi>Samſon</hi> ſhould not haue dyed, if wiſdome could doe yt <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſhould not haue dyed if riches, dainty fare, and gorgeous arraye could doe it. <hi>Diues</hi> ſhould not haue dyed if zeal diligent diſcharge of calling could doe it, <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould not haue dyed: if ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie and chaſtity could doe it, <hi>Mary</hi> the holy &amp; bleſſed virgin ſhould not haue dyed at a word, if monarchies, &amp; lordſhips cold deliuer from death, <hi>Cyrus, Alexander,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould not haue died, And therfore <hi>Horace</hi> tells his frend <hi>Torquatus,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his glas is run down, &amp; his race finiſhed,
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Car. lib, <hi>4.</hi> Ode, <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note>Non Torquate genus, non te facundia, non te Reſtituet pietas:</q> It was not his noble deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, it was not his pleaſant and eloquent tounge, it was not his virtuous life that coulde reſtore &amp; recall his dayes. A Ieſuit, our countrima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeakes of a company of religious men in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6972:15"/> 
               <hi>Rome,</hi> which ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly calld the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of dead men, &amp; they ſeldom or neuer ar ſeen abroad but in rare &amp; extraordinary proceſſions, &amp; wher they goe, they carry y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pourtraiture of death made after a gaſtly &amp; greeſly ſhape, &amp; this written by it, <hi>nemi ni parco.</hi> I ſpare and forbear none.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Turnerus Deuonius.</hi> Heb, 9, 27.</note> I wold himſelfe &amp; the reſt of the maſſing Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts did alway behold that picture: for if they remembred, that it is appoynted for al men to dy once; &amp; then cometh the iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment: it were meruelous, if they did not begyn to be aſhamed of their pride, theire compaſſing of the ſea &amp; land, to make <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Proſelytes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be twofold more y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of hell (if it were poſſible) then them ſelues are.<note place="margin">Mat. 23.15.</note> Thus you ſee that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> generally ar miſerable &amp; mortal both the godly &amp; vngodly.</p>
            <p>But why ar the godly commonly more af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flicted then others? for it is ſayd of the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> to <hi>Iohn.</hi>
               <note place="margin">v, 14.</note> 
               <hi>that they came out of great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> This is not for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god doth forget them, or for that god cannot or wil not de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liver the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly out of all da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, but for that god loues them more then other and draws them neerer and neerer to himſelfe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6972:16"/> by chaſtiſement and correction, Conſider the profitable working, that tribulation and affliction hath in the godly; and who will not aſcribe it to gods ſinguler loue, that they are afflicted ſometimes more then other, to receiue thereby alwayes more prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it then other? Firſt tribulation ſtirs vs vp to repentance for ſin, and is a ſermon to amendement of life. For the godly are afflicted for their ſins; not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſatiſfie gods iuſtice; but to confeſſe their offences, and to acknowledge theyr iniquities, and to be purged ftom their faults, and by temporary correction to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde the eternall deſtruction of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.<note place="margin">1 Cor: 11:32:</note> God giueth the raynes to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that they may fall into perdition; and he beſtowes vppon them the bleſſinges of this life, and the fleeting and ſhort ioyes thereof, becauſe they are his creatures, to the end hee may make them inexcuſable, and conuict them of ingratitude: but hee amends and reclaims his children by the croſſe and tribulation. For as the Vrchin or Hedghog folded vp round together in his prickly ſkin, ſeems not poſſible to bee opened without killing and flaying it of:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6972:16"/> and yet if hot water be ſprinkled on it, it opens it ſelfe immediately: ſo ſome that are ſo hardned and wrapped vp in the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of ſinning, as it ſeemes, that death only may end their vngodlines, yet when the hote water of tribulation is powred vpon them, they are ſoftned and diſſolued, and made open to repentance. This hote water had ſuch an effectuall operation in <hi>Dauid</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he cryed, <hi>Saue me o god for the waters are entred euen to my ſoule.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 69:1:</note> Againe tribulation tries our faith, as the fire tries gold: and as the fyning pot tries ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and as the hammer diſcernes the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the mettal. For as gold hath a cleer ſound vnder the hammer, and ſpreades much before it crack, but braſſe ſoundes harſhly and breakes quickly: ſo the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full endure the hammering of tribulation and yeelde foorth the ſweete praiſes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hankſgiuing: but the vngodly repine, and murmur,<note place="margin">Pari motu exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exhalat horribiliter coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num; &amp; ſuaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fragrat vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum. Aug. de Ciuit. dei, lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> and bewray their vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and crack when they are brought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ammering. Stir puddle, and it wil ſmell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>othſomly: ſtir a ſweet ointement, and it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill ſmell fragrantly: euen ſo affliction <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>akes the godly to bleſſe god, and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6972:17"/> makes the vngodly to blaſpheme god. Beſides this, tribulation breeds patience and exerciſeth patience,<note place="margin">Iames 1.3:4:</note> that it may haue her perfect working, and may be intire, and lack nothing. Tribulation works hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility in vs, and knowledge of our ſelues, and a learning of obedience, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes of Chriſt: that <hi>though he were ſonne, yet he learned obedience, by the things which he ſuffered.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb: 5.8</note> Tribulation cauſeth vs to long for heauen, and to loathe the world, and not to loue the things of the world, and not to repoſe confidence in the loue of the world:<note place="margin">1 Iohn 2:15</note> for as the world hated Chriſt, ſo it hateth the godly that beleeue in chriſt: and becauſe the godlye are not of the worlde, therefore the world hateth them. Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation makes vs the members,<note place="margin">Iohn. 13, 18 19</note> conforme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to chriſt our head, that we may fulfill the reſt of the afflictions of Chriſt in the fleſh:<note place="margin">Col. 1.29.</note> and that he that ſanctifieth, and they that are ſanctified, may be all of one. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation makes for the honour,<note place="margin">Heb, 2.10.</note> and praiſe and glory of god, in that god workes deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance out of affliction: and though hee kill, yet he makes aliue: and though hee bring downe to the graue,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2:6:</note> yet hee rayſeth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6972:17"/> vp; and though the godly are afflicted on euery ſide, yet they are not in diſtreſſe; though they are in doubte, yet they deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre not: though they are perſecuted, yet they are not forſaken: though they are caſt downe, yet they periſh not.<note place="margin">2. Cor, 4.8, 9</note> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, tribulation is a teſtimony and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the iudgemente to come, and of euerlaſting life; for the iuſtice and trueth of GOD require, that at length the good ſhould be comforted, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked puniſhed: but for that this is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes doon in this life, therefore it ſhall be perfourmed when the Lord Ieſus ſhall ſhew himſelf from heauen with his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Angells.<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 1.7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> And the tribulation of the faithfull ſhould excite, and prouoke the wicked, to ſhake off their ſins, that ſtick ſo faſt vnto him: For if the time be come, that iudgement muſt begin at the houſe of god what ſhall the end bee of them that obeye not the Goſpell of God? and if the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſcarcely be ſaued, where ſhall the vngodly and the ſinner appeer? and if this be done in the green tre,<note place="margin">1 Pe, 4:17, 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Luke 23, 31</note> what ſhalbe done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dry tree? for if chriſt, the green &amp; flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing tree of righteouſneſſe, and the godly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6972:18"/> that are braunches of the ſame tree, did and doe ſuffer great tribulation; what ſhoulde the vnrepentant and wicked ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, (that are dry, withered, and fruitles trees,) but conſuming fire, and the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the iuſt iudgement of God?</p>
            <p>Yea but doth not the prouidence of god ſleep, will ſome ſay; when the godly are greatly afflicted? and how doth god acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh this promiſe, that hee will ſhrowde them, and couer them, and protect them, and pitch a tent about them, and <hi>dwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them?</hi> certainly he that keeps <hi>Iſrael</hi> doth neither ſlumber nor ſleep: the lord is the keeper of his children,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 121.4.5.</note> and their ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow at their right hand: he ayds them by the power of his grace, and he giues them that <hi>comforter,</hi> that ſhal abide with them for euer:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh: 14. v. 16</note> he wil not leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as deſtitute <hi>Orphanes,</hi> but he wil come to them, and aſſiſt them;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.23.</note> he will lodge with them, and make continuall abode with them, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth their fayth, that they may neuer doubt of his loue, but ſtill depend vppon him. Can a woman forget her childe, and not haue compaſſion on the ſonne of her wombe? though ſhe ſhould forget her ſons,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6972:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> yet the Lorde will not forgette his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.<note place="margin">Eſai 49, 15</note> Many are the troubles of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; true:<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.20</note> but the Lorde deliuers them out of all. The godlye are much preſſed; true; but they flouriſhe as the <hi>Palme</hi> tree;<note place="margin">Pſal: 92.12</note> which the more it is preſſed downe, the more it ſprouteth vp. The rayne falls, and the floodes come, and the windes blowe on the faythfull; true: but theyr houſe falls not,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.24:</note> becauſe it is builte on a rocke?<note place="margin">poieſei te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ekbaſin</note> God ſuffers his children to be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; true: but he is faithfull and will not ſuffer them to be tempted aboue that they are able;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but will euen with the tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on giue the iſſue and way out, that they may be able to beare it.<note place="margin">Mat. 20:22</note> Chriſt calls affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and tribulation, <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> for that as in Baptiſme, wee are dipped downe into the water, but not drowned, or choaked in the water; ſo though wee bee waſhed with the water of tribulation, yet wee are not ouerwhelmed therein. And as <hi>Noah</hi> was preſerued from the greate daunger of the flood, when hee and his familye were incloſed in the Arke, and the reſt did periſh that were out of the Arke:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.20:</note> ſo whoſoeuer in the church of God doe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6972:19"/> and cleaue to Chriſt, though they bee loaden with calamities, yet at length in due ſeaſon they are deliuered: whereas others that are out of the church, are ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp by the flood of ſinne, and of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmentes that accompanye ſinne. How greeuouſly was <hi>Job</hi> vexed by the <hi>Sabeans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1, 15.16.17 &amp; 2.7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: 42.12, &amp;c <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es. 5:11</note> by fire from heauen, by the <hi>Chaldaeans,</hi> by Sathan, by his wife: yet how gloriouſlie was he at laſt deliuered? And as round bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies, that are in all parts equally circular may reſt, and be ſetled on eache parte and ſide: ſo the godly are conſtant in whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eſtate: for the Lord puts his hand vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, to make their reſting place eaſie and commodious, as the Prophet ſayes:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m 37, 24</note> 
               <hi>Though they fall, they ſhall not bee caſt off: for the Lord putteth vnder his hand</hi> When the ſtaie and ſtrength is taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vngodly, when they ſhal bee oppreſſed one of another, when woe ſhall be to the wicked, and euill ſhall be with them, and the rewarde of their hands ſhall be giuen them:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10:</note> then, then, <hi>ſurelie it ſhall be wel with the iuſt.</hi> For all thinges worke together for the beſt vnto them that loue God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 8.28 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c.</note> in tribulation and anguiſhe, in famyne and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6972:19"/> nakedneſſe, in perill and ſworde, they are more then conquerours through him that loued them. For wee are perſwaded, that neither deathe nor life: nor Angells, nor principalities, nor powers: nor thinges preſent, nor thinges to come: nor heighth, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall bee able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſince god is ready to help in tribulation, and hath promiſed to bee with vs in trouble, and to deliuer vs,<note place="margin">Pſalm 91 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that wee may glorifie him, and hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to call vppon him in the day of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie: let vs ſubmit our ſelues vnto god, and drawe neere vnto God,<note place="margin">Iames 4.7:<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 10 &amp; 5:13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> with zealous praier, and hee will drawe neere vnto vs: and lift vs vppe. And ſince affliction is the portion and lotte of all the godlie, that falls out to them, and attendes on them: when wee ſee our Brethren endure tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, wee muſt not preſentlye cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them, to bee hated and vtterlie forſaken of GOD: but rather recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the ſignes of Gods fauour towardes them. For hee that ſayes,<note place="margin">Nihil aliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cit, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non conue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aduerſariu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Baſil in Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6972:20"/> godly ought not to ſuffer tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; ſaies this; that a wreſtler ſhoulde not haue an aduerſary to encounter him: and if a wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtler ſtriue not, what garland or glory can he obtaine? and ſince none of the faithfull haue an immunity and priuiledge from af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, but haue them ſelues dronke at one or other tyme of the cup of tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for as noyſome and peſtilent beaſtes (ſaith <hi>Baſil</hi>) ſeeke after a praye,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t animalia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a, nos aeru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etere at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt. Baſil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. <hi>45</hi>
               </note> and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe not, til they haue found it, ſo miſeries continually hunt after the godly, and find them at length: this muſt teach vs, to ſhew commiſeration on the afflicted, and not to turne our eye from our owne fleſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our ſelues knowe the weighte of affliction; following the example of Chriſt our Sauiour, who is an highe Prieſte, which can ſympathize and bee touched with the feeling of our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, becauſe in all things he was temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in lyke ſort, yet without ſin. Fynally ſince tribulation muſt needs trie the faith and patience of the godly,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1415.</note> that after they haue bin tryed, they may receiue the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe; let vs not murmur nor grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble againſt our heauenly Father, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6972:20"/> vs for our profite. If the earthlye Fathers of our bodyes, correct vs, yet we reuerence them: for though Fathers put their ſonnes out of their ſighte, and binde them to huſbandry, or employ them in an handycraft, or beſtowe them in marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, or ſend them into the wars, yet the ſonnes are well content, becauſe it makes for their prefermente and aduantage, <hi>ſhould not we much rather be in ſubiection vnto the father of ſpirites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12:9:</note> 
               <hi>that wee might lyue? A Generall</hi> enioyns perilous ſeruice to none but moſt valiant ſouldiers, and thoſe that hee loues beſt and whome hee woulde aduance; for them hee ſends out to lye in ambuſh for the enemye; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſh ſome fort, or to inuade the mayne army of the foe. Not one of thoſe that are ſo ſent foorth, ſayes: the <hi>Generall</hi> hath doone mee wrong, or wiſhes me not well; vnleſſe perhappes he be a coward and faintehearted: but contrarilye, if hee bee valorous, and woorthye of the name of a Souldier, hee ſayeth thus; the Generall thinkes well of me, hee hath a good opinion of mee; hee fauours mee; and ſeeks to honour mee, So is the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6972:21"/> caſe betweene GOD and vs.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.24</note> Out life in this worlde is a warfare, and wee all runn in a race, let vs therefore ſtriue and fight againſte all afflictions, that the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God bringes vppon vs:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 25</note> that when wee haue ſtriued as wee oughte to doe, we may bee crowned; that when wee haue fought a good fighte, and finiſhed our courſe, and kept the faith, the crowne of righteouſneſſe may bee layed vppe for vs; that when wee haue reioyced in tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 4.7, 8</note> (knowing that tribulation bringeth foorthe patience,<note place="margin">Rom 5, 3, 4, 5,</note> &amp; patience experience, &amp; experience hope, &amp; hope maketh not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) at laſte wee may come out of tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, vnto the glorious inheritaunce of the Saintes in lighte. And thus far of the ſtate and condition of the faithfull in this life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſtate of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he godly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er this life.</note>Now let vs come to the ſtate &amp; condition of the godly, after they are departed out of this world. It is ſaid here by the Angell, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they hunger no more, neither thirſte any more, &amp; that the ſun ſhall not light on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any more, neither any heate. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lambe which is in the mids of the throne ſhal feed &amp; gouerne them, &amp; ſhall leade them to the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6972:21"/> fountaines of waters:<note place="margin">v,, 16, 17,</note> and god ſhall wipe awaie al teares from their eies. The ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and honorable names that are giuen to the place, where the faythful are after death, doe throughly manifeſt the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of their eſtate. For it is called in holy ſcripture ſometimes a kingdome; ſometimes the boſome of Abraham, ſometimes <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> ſometimes a place of many manſions; ſometimes reſte, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes the new <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſometimes a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, And al theſe titles do declare vnto vs the ſurpaſſing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort which the godly receaue, when they are freed from this wretched worlde. It is called a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, where Chriſt ſayeth to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>feare not little flock,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 12, 32.</note> 
               <hi>for it is your fathers pleaſure to giue you the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> In which words our Sauiour v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a moſte forcible argument to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe vs from impiety and carefulneſſe for earthly thinges, and diſtruſting Gods prouidence, that wee ſhal wante things requiſite for this preſent life: for hee that giues the greater and better thinge will not denye the leſſer and inferior; ſens the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our heauenly father hath
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6972:22"/> of his owne grace and pleaſure prouided the kingdome of heauen for vs;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n baſileian</note> let vs not doubte, but hee will giue all other things vnto vs. And albeit our ſtate in this worlde, be oftentimes baſe, &amp; needy, and miſerable: yet wee muſt refreſhe our ſoules with the remembrance of that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly kingdome, in which at length wee ſhall raign with Chriſt: and gloriouſly tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>umph ouer Sathan, death, &amp; bell through Chriſt, if vnfainedly we beleeue in chriſt. It is called <hi>Abrahams boſome,</hi> where Chriſte ſayth, that when the beggar <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> dyed, he was caryed of the Angells into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke. 16, 22.</note> Hee was caryed of the Angells; for that as Angells, are all miniſtring Spirits,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb 1, 14.</note> ſent fourth to miniſter, for their ſakes which ſhall bee heires of ſaluation, and doe ſafegarde the godly by the lords apointment from ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry daungers of this mortall life: ſo it is their charge &amp; parte to conuay into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoules of the righteous, when they are looſed from the fetters of the fleſh. And as infants doe reſt quietly in their mothers boſome, ſo heauen is a receptacle and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for the faithfull, in which they take
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6972:22"/> their quiet reſt and eaſe,<note place="margin">Caluin in Har.</note> after the ſturres of this tumultuary life ar ended. And it is called <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome becauſe as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am</hi> was a moſt conſtant beleeuer,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11 Gal, 3, 7,</note> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oue hope beleeued vnder hope, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore is calld the father of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beleeuers, ſo whoſoeuer deſire to be gathered into that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſome after this life they muſt in this life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mitate &amp; follow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith &amp; godlines of faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful <hi>Abraham.</hi> It is called <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Sauiour ſayth to the penitent theefe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the croſſe <hi>to day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradice:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke, 23.43. <hi>Gell lib,</hi> 20, <hi>cap</hi> 20,</note> the <hi>Greeks</hi> vſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> word <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diſe</hi> for a place y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is hedged round,<note place="margin">The glory of God is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnder the figures of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed things: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we can not elſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it: as the puniſhments of the wicked are deſcribed by fire. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt cals the ſtate of eternall life Paradiſe. Cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uin in Har.</note> wherin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or pleaſure, either pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and trees are ſet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rels beaſts ar paſtured and commonly it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s vſed for a garden repleniſhed with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iety of delights ſuch as was the garden of <hi>Eden</hi> in which <hi>Adam</hi> was placed. And as the 70. Interpreters called the garden of <hi>Eden by that name,</hi> ſo Chriſt calls hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en Paradiſe, for that as a Garden is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raught with fair flowers and fragrant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earbes and delitious fruites &amp; ſtore of pleaſures, ſo heauen is a place aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing with true bleſſednes, and the perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of euery good thing which may bee
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6972:23"/> imagined, loued or deſired. <hi>Paul</hi> cals it <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radiſe,</hi> or the third heauen, into which he was taken,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Cor. 12, 2,</hi> Beza &amp; Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat in eum locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> &amp; heard words which cannot be ſpoken, and which are not poſſible for man to vtter: Where (without inſiſting on the <hi>Empyreall</hi> heauen, of which Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers trifle and make much diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Mat. 6, 26, Mat, 24, 29,</note>) wee muſt marke that the ſcripture makes mention of three heauens, one in which the byrdes flye, called alſo the aie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> another in which the ſtars and ſphears of the heauen are ſetled,<note place="margin">Acts 3.2, Phil. 3, 20. Col, 3,.. Matth, 18, 10 Luke, 16.22. Theſ, 4, 27,</note> and the third, called of Chriſt &amp; Paul <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> in which chriſt lyued, and the holy <hi>Angels,</hi> &amp; the bleſſed ſoules of thoſe that depart out of this life in the faith of Chriſt, to which chriſt aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which he ſhal come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> generall iudgment: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bodyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful may be taken vp thither, to remaine with the lord for euer: It is calld an houſe of many manſions, or dwelling places: where our Sauiour ſaith to his diſciples, <hi>in my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe of my dwellinge places. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> compares the actions of our life in this world,<note place="margin">Iohn 14.2,</note> to the ſportes and playes of little children, that build ſmall ſporting houſes, and addreſſe counterfaite
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6972:23"/> banquetings to paſſe the time withall.<note place="margin">Homil, <hi>24,</hi> in Matthaeum</note> For many times they gather fiſheſe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hels and clay, and when they haue fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med therwith their imaginary cells, they glory in them after their manner aſmuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s they which haue erected lofty galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes and ſtately dining chambers. But as theſe conceiued workes periſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd quickly fall, and men laugh when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey behold children weeping for their fal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o our buildings and complots in this life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re ruinous and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitory, and if we were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome to the perfect age of men in chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhould perceiue, that all theſe are chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſh things, and we would beſtow all our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndeuour in ſeeking to attaine to thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xed and vnchaungeable dwelling places a heauen. For as they that are made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orthy to be once poſſeſſors of thoſe dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng places, euer remaine and abide in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> alſo are they eternall, and not fading <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> earthly manſions and worldly habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons, but they are that immortal inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce, and vndefiled, &amp; that withreth not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſerued in heauen for vs.<note place="margin">1, Pet. 1.4,</note> It is called reſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d quietneſſe, for ſo the moſte hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enly oracle cryed to Iohn; <hi>Write
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6972:24"/> the dead which die in the Lord from hence foorth bleſſed: euen ſo ſayeth the ſpirite, for they reſte from their labours, and their works followe them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 14, 13.</note> And the way that leades to this bleſſed reſt from all labours, is the way of peace: in which old Symeon thriſtingly deſired to departe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when he had embraced Chriſt Ieſus in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his armes and had ſeene the ſaluation of God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had ſo long wayted for. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at reſt haue the godly in this worlde,<note place="margin">Luke, 2, 28, 29</note> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they continually labour, and trauell, and ſtriue, &amp; wraſtle, for the combate betwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Spirite and the fleſh ceaſeth not, while we dwell heere in theſe houſes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> claye. For though we delight in the law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God, concerning the inner man, wee ſee another law in our members, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt the law of our minde, &amp; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vs captiue into the lawe of ſinne, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that though we would do good, yet we are ſo yoaked that euil is preſent with vs, and though to will be preſent with vs, yet w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> finde no meanes to performe that which is good, for in vs, that is in our fleſh dwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth no good thinge: &amp; wee cannot allo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that which we doe;<note place="margin">Rom. 7.15,</note> for what wee woulde
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6972:24"/> that we doe not, but what wee hate,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.15 &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that doe we. What is there in the world, but a perpetuall fight againſt ſathan and ſinne and a dayly conflict againſt darts &amp; wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pons?<note place="margin">Cyprian de mortalit. <hi>4</hi>
               </note> We haue a dayly &amp; continuall and troubleſome contending with couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, with incontinency, with anger, with ambition with worldly and fleſhly cares &amp; ſnares. Our minds are ſo ſtraightlie be fiedged with an army of vices; as that it is hard to reſiſte and withſtand all iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> couetouſnes is ouerthrown: luſt riſeth vp: when luſt is ſubdued, ambition comes in place, when ambition is chaſed, anger gaules the minde pride pufs vppe, drunkenneſſe tempts, enuy breaks concord ſuſpition diſioynes friendſhip. The godly mind thus daily ſuffering, thus daylye preſſed,<note place="margin">Illa noſtra pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> illa fida tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitas, illa ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bilis, &amp; firma et perpetua ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curiras.</note> thus dailye ſtanding among the ſwords of Satan: how happy is ſhe, when ſhe mounts to the reſt of heauen, where our peace is, our ſure tranquility, our ſtable, firme, and euerlaſting ſecurity. It is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the heauenly and new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal, 4.26, Reu. 3.12.</note> to expreſſe and repreſent vnto vs the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable &amp; vnconceaueable ioyes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For although the old <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> was a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6972:25"/> moſt beautiful place, euen the glory of the whole earth, being invironed with ſtrong walls, defended by the inuincible mount <hi>Sion,</hi> enriched with infinite treaſure, dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with all externall brauery; yet it loſt her glory; and her pomp periſhed, and it be came an heape of ſtones, and it was forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of God, and made an hiſſing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible by-worde to euery nation vnder heauen. But in this heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the ſacred trinity will abide for euer: and thoſe foundations of the wall garniſhed with pretious ſtones, thoſe gates which are pearles, &amp; that pretious ſhining as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iaſpar and Chriſtall, &amp; thoſe ſtreets of pure golde, as ſhining glaſſe: and that brightnes that needs no ſunne nor moone to ſhine in it, and that pure riuer of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life; and that tree of life, which gyues fruite euery month,<note place="margin">Reu. 21. &amp;. 22,</note> &amp; whoſe leaues ſerue to heale the nations with; do vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſcure, and eclipſe, and extinguiſhe the glorious dignity of the old <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> Laſt of all it is called that city which the faithful ſeeke after, for we haue heere no continuing city, but we ſeeke one to come ſayeth the apoſtle.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>The Greekes,</hi> call a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6972:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> their toung. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be cauſe it conſiſteth of many inhabiters Howe many the citizens of heauen are maye be gathered by the former viſion; when Iohn ſawe a greate multitude ſealed with the ſeale of the liuing God, of all nations and kindreds, and people, &amp; toungs, which no man could number.<note place="margin">Reu. 7, 9</note> For they which haue made their long robes white in the blood of the lambe;<note place="margin">Heb: 12, 22.23.24,</note> doe come vnto mounte Syon, and to the city of the liuing God the celeſtiall <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and to the companye of innumerable Angels, and to the aſſembly and congregation of the firſt borne which are written in heauen,<note place="margin">Cum quibus in praeſentia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctiſumus vinculo charita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis ibi conſortio aeterno coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendi. Aug En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chirid, cap, <hi>56.</hi> Intelligit ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas a corpori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſeparatas et in coelum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptas, Piſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, in ſchol. cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin in ep, ad, <hi>Heb.</hi> c. <hi>12</hi> Iun i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> paral.</note> and to God the Iudge of all: and to the ſpirits of iuſt and perfect men, and to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the mediator of the new teſtament, &amp; to the bloude of the ſprinkling, that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth better things then that of <hi>Abel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They that are with Chriſt, are moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, for Chriſt is bleſſedneſſe, and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and immortalitye it ſelfe: and are not the true beleeuers then moſte bleſſed, ſince they are with Chriſte af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life, where hee is? vnles wee will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oubt of this, that god the father heard y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:6972:26"/> prayer of his beloued ſonne,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Heb. Naz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Orat. de, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Gorg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn, 17, 24,</hi>
               </note> thus pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his choſen; <hi>Father, I will that they which thou haſt giuen mee, bee with mee euen where <hi>I</hi> am, that they maye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde that my glory, which thou haſt giuen mee?</hi> Heere the brightnes of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dlineſſe and true virtue it ſelfe is many times dazeled and darkened; partly by enuy, partly by pouerty, partly by ſlanders and the like croſſes, but in heauen godlineſſe ſhall glitter and ſhine in her perfecte brightnes:<note place="margin">Dan, 12, 3,</note> for there the wiſe ſhall ſhine, as the brightneſſe of the firmamente, and they that turne many to righteouſneſſe ſhall ſhine as the ſtarres, for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and the iuſt ſhall ſhine as the ſunne in the Kingdome of their father.<note place="margin">Mat, 13, 43,</note> Heere wee are continually ſubiect to feare, and anguiſhe, and ſorrowe, and death lies e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in ambuſh for vs, in heauen death ſhall haue no place.<note place="margin">Iſai, 25:8,</note> But the godly being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from the bondage of corruption ſhall participate of the glorious liberty of the ſonnes of god.<note place="margin">Rom, 8.21,</note> Heer it is delectable to beholde faier palaces, more delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to enter into them, and to bee enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them, moſt delectable to dwell
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6972:26"/> in them alwayes, and to behold the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the lord of them neuer chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged towards vs, but ſtill gratious and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable: how delectable then is it, to behoulde the radiant palace of heauen; and to be an inhabiter in it, and neuer to goe out of it, and continually to beholde the gratious and omnipotent Maieſty of God therein? for though we are now the ſonnes of God, yet it is not made manifeſt what we ſhalbe,<note place="margin">opſometha a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kathos eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and we know that when he ſhalbe made manifeſt, we ſhall bee like him; <hi>For we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> Here we know in part, and we propheſy in part;<note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> we ſpeak as children; we vnderſtand as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; we think as children, we ſee thorow a glaſſe darkly; but in heauen that which is in part ſhalbe aboliſhed; childiſh things ſhalbe put away; we ſhall ſee face to face, &amp; know euen as we are known, we ſhall meet together (in the vnity of faith,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.9 &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and that acknowledging of the ſonne of God) vnto a perfect man, and vnto the meaſure of the age of the fulneſſe of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.13</note> Heere in this life wee are regenerate and newe borne by the holy ſpirite of God; for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe none can ſee the kingdome of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6972:27"/> God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 3, 3, 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar, 9, 24,</note> nor enter into it, but as long as wee lyue heere, we are regenerate but in part and wee are reſtored but in parte to the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God after which Adam was at firſt created; after this life in heauen ſhall be the perfect renewing of the image of God in vs, and euerlaſting comforte, and abundance enioying of all good thinges which are required to the ſtate of entyre felicity.</p>
            <p>While wee liue heere, eternall lyfe is begon in vs, in that our myndes are endewed with true and ſauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of god, and fayth in Ieſus Chriſte, (for, this is eternal life to knowe god, and whome he hath ſent Ieſus Chriſte, &amp; he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heareth the word of chriſt, and beleeueth in him that ſent him, hath euerlaſting lyfe) and in that the lyfe which wee doe lyue being engraffed into chriſte by the ſpirite,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hn, 17, 3: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hn, 5, 24, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hn, 3, 16, 36 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al, 2, 20, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol, 3, 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h, 4, 18, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 1.4, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol, 3.4.</note> is <hi>the life of god,</hi> and a participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the diuine nature: &amp; further, while we liue heere, we are aſſured of eternall life, that when Chriſt ſhall appeare: wee ſhallbee alſo with him in glory, and that he which hath begunne that good worke in vs, will alſo make it perfect, euen vntil
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6972:27"/> the daye of Ieſus chriſt;<note place="margin">Phil. 1, 6. 1. Cor. 1, 8, Thoſſe, 5, 23 Rom, 11, 29, Iob, 10, 28, 2, Tim, 1, 12, Iohn, 14, 23, Iohn, 14, 16, Iohn, 17:3, Luke, 20, 36, Iohn, 16, 22, 1, Cor, 15, 28 Reu, 21, 22, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1, Cor. 13, 10 Luke, 1.33; Dan. 7, 27.</note> and that the gifts and calling of God are without repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; vnchaungeable, &amp; that none can plucke Chriſts ſheepe out of his hands, for wee knowe whome wee haue beleeued, &amp; wee are perſwaded that hee is able to keepe that which we haue committed vnto hym but the perfecting of theſe beginnings is reſerued for the kingdom of heauen, wher god ſhall dwell in his elect eternally, where that comforter ſhall neuer forſake vs; where ſhal be perfect wyſedom &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of God where ſhall be angelike righteouſneſſe, where ſhall be vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ioyes in god, where ſhall be abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of all good things for God, ſhalbe all in al things where that which is now but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne, ſhal be finiſhed and abſolute, and where there ſhal be noe interruption, and end of ioy and gladneſſe for of that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome there ſhall be none end and an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting dominion ſhall be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy people of the moſt high. And herevpon not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out caus doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet ſet his chiefeſt felicity in this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lord is the portion of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; therfore he ſayth: <hi>I <hi>ſet the lord always before me, becaus he is on my right
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6972:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> hande, therefore I ſhall not fall, therefore my hearte reioyced, alſo my fleſh ſhall reſte in hope, thou wilt ſhewe mee the path of lyfe,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal 16.5, 8, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.11,</note> 
               <hi>and the fulneſſe of ioyes is in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and at thy righte hand, pleaſures for euermore.</hi> As if he had ſayed: thou wilte grante me, that hauing runne ouer the race of this fleeting and fraile life, I ſhall enioy that moſt ioyfull, moſte pleaſante, &amp; eternal life in thine heauenlye kingdom. Auguſtine ſayeth, that in heauen ſhall bee the euerlaſting Sabbath, which noe Eueninge ſhall end. <hi>There wee ſhall reſt and wee ſhall ſee; wee ſhall ſee and wee ſhall loue; wee ſhall loue, and wee ſhall prayſe, Behoulde</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that which is in the ende is withoute end. <hi>Nam quis alius noſter est finis, niſi peruenire ad regnum cuius nullus est finis.</hi>
               </hi> For what other end is there ordained for the Godly; but to attaine to that Kingedome which hath none end? Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byll ſayeth,<note place="margin">Aug de Ciu, dei lib, <hi>22,</hi> c, <hi>30,</hi>
               </note> that it ſhall not bee ſayed in heauen. <hi>The nighte is come: or to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe ſhall come, or yeſterday is paſte, neither ſhall there bee that daye that is wearied with cares, nor ſpring, nor ſummer
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6972:28"/> nor Autumne nor winter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
            </q>
            <p>There ſhall be noe mariage, nor death no ſelling nor buying, nor ſunne ryſing, nor Sunſetting, for God ſhall make that longe daye which ſhall bee end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.<note place="margin">Sibill, Orac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib, <hi>7;</hi>
               </note> There ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſo many and ſuch ioys, as al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Arithmeticians of this world are not able to number them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metritians</hi> are not able to weigh them: all the <hi>Grammarians, Logitians, Rhetoritians</hi> are not able to expreſſe them in fit terms. For as the Apoſtle <hi>Saint Paule</hi> doth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the thinges which God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed for them that loue him, are ſuch as eye hath not ſeene, neither eare hath heard neither came into any mans heart. There ſhall be ioy aboue vs,<note place="margin">1, Cor, 2, 9,</note> for the viſion which wee ſhall ſee, there, likewiſe ſhall bee ioye vnder vs for the beawtie of the heauens and other corporall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, there ſhall be ioy within and about vs, for the felowſhippe and companye of Saintes, and Angeles. There Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons wiſedome ſhall be reputed but foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe; <hi>Abſoloms</hi> beautie but deformity <hi>Azaels</hi> ſwiftneſſe but ſlowneſſe: <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:6972:29"/> might but weakneſſe;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hom. Aquin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e uer, Theol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, <hi>7.</hi> chap. <hi>6,</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mathuſelaes</hi> lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g life but frailty, the kingdome of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> but beggery. The ſaints would not ſo earneſtly haue longed after heauen had they not beene aſſured of the ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge ioyes thereof. <hi>Dauid</hi> being hindred by his perſecuters that he could not bee preſent amonge gods people in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> he ſhewes his feruent de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſire towardes that place, in which hee mighte ſerue the Lorde, ſaying: <hi>as the hart brayeth for the ryuers of water, ſo pan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth my ſoul after thee O god: my ſoul thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth for god, euen for the liuing god: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal <hi>I</hi> com &amp; appear befor</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god?</hi> And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was exiled &amp; driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.2.</note> and could not come to the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of the Lorde and the aſſembly of the ſaints to prayſe god, how vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth hee bewraye how hee was affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned thitherwarde. <hi>O Lorde of hoaſtes</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>how amiable are thy taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; My ſoule longeth, yea and fainteth for the Courtes of the lorde. Bleſſed are they that dwell in thine houſe, they will euer prayſe thee. For a day in thy courts is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d otherwher <hi>I</hi> had rather
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6972:29"/> bee a doorekeeper in the houſe of my god,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.1.2.4.10.</note> 
               <hi>then to dwell in the tabernacles of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> If the Prophet did ſo long &amp; thirſt, pante and faynte after the materiall and tranſitory temple of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> on earth; how was hee enflamed with a deſire to come to the ſpirituall and eternall temple of the Lord in heauen? When our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was tranſfigured on the mountaine, and his face did ſhine as the ſunn, and his clothes were as white as the lighte, and there appeared <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> talking with him, <hi>Peter</hi> rauiſhed with this celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all apparition, ſayd to Ieſus, <hi>Maſter it is good for vs to be heere: if thou wilt, let vs make here three Tabernacles; one for thee, and one for Moſes, and one for Elias.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 17.1.8</note> If the Apoſtle were ſo tranſported with a ſlender view and ſmall taſte of heauenly felicity, as that hee deſired alwaye to adhere and cleaue vnto it; what would he haue donne, if he had beene fully entered into his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ioy? <hi>Hierom</hi> notes vpon theſe words of <hi>Peter,</hi> that Chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alone way to go to the glory and ioyes of heauen; &amp; that wee muſt build &amp; pitch a tabernacle for him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our heartes; and that we muſt hear &amp;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6972:30"/> obey him only; as the voyce from heauen taught <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, 17 5</note> and in <hi>Peter</hi> the reſt of the Apoſtles, and all beleeuers; and therefore he is bold to ſay to <hi>Peter, erras Petre, ſicut &amp; alias euangeliſta teſtatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e eidos he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gei <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uke 9, 33</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>neſcis quid di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas:</hi> thou art deceiued <hi>Peter;</hi> &amp; as another Euangeliſt witneſſeth, thou knoweſt not what thou ſayſt; ſeeke not three Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieron. in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent in cap <hi>17,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>att:</note> when there is but one tabernacle of the Goſpell, in which <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> the law and the prophets are compriſed and briefely repeated. This ioyfull inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of heauen made <hi>Paul</hi> to ſay, <hi>I counte that the afflictions of this preſente time are not worthy of the glory, which ſhalbe ſhewed vnto vs:</hi> and againe. <hi>our light affliction which is but for a moment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om 8.18</note> 
               <hi>cauſeth vnto vs a far more excellent and an eternall weight of glory: while we looke not on the things which are ſeen, but on the things which are not ſeene: for the things which are ſeene are temporall, but the things which are not ſeen are eternall:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cor. 4.17.18</note> and againe; <hi>Chriſt is to mee both in life and in death aduantage: &amp; whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to liue in the fleſh were profitable for me, and what to chuſe I know not: for I am diſtreſſed betweene both; and (though to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6972:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the fleſh is more needefull for the Church of chriſt,) J deſire to be looſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1, 21, 22 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>and to be with chriſt, which is beſt of all.</hi> And therefore the militant Church, and ſpouſe of Chriſt alwaies ſeekes Chriſt her belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, in the night and troubles of this life; and in the ſtreets, and open places; and wartes, and labours euery where to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all opportunities to imbrace him and doth neuer ſuffer him to depart from her, till the day breake,<note place="margin">Can. 3, 1, 2, 3</note> and the ſhadowes flee away that is,<note place="margin">Nec cum in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tus fuerit, ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bitur a quar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do: non ped<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> paſſibus, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſideriis quaeri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur Deus. Ec vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non ext dit deſideriu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fanctum foel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inuentio, ſed tendit. Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſummati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gaudu, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> consumptio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Oleum magi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> illi: nam ips<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> flamma. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Can ser. <hi>8 Heb. 11:36.</hi>
               </note> till the darkeſome and yrkſom life bee ended; and that glorious appearing of Chriſt come, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church ſhal be perfectly taken into the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt, and ſhall gloriouſly enioy all good things. For when the faithfull ſoule hath found Chriſt, <hi>ſhe ceaſeth not from ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: God is not ſought by feete, but by affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and the happy finding of him dooth not ſhake off, but encreaſe an holy deſire. Is the conſummation of ioy, a conſumption of deſire? No: it is rather as oyle vnto it, for this deſire is a burning flame,</hi> ſayeth <hi>Bernard,</hi> And what cauſed the ſaints and Martirs, whome the world was not woorthy of, to ſuffer mockings and ſcourgings, bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6972:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> priſonment; to wander vp and downe in ſheepe ſkinnes, and in goats ſkins, in wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idetur legen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um eſſe epuras <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heſan, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cremati sunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un. in parall.</note> and mountaines, and caues, and dennes of the earth; to endure to be ſtoned, and hewen aſunder, and burned, and ſlayn with the ſworde; and yet in the mids of tortures to ſay with the Chriſtian poet,
<q>
                  <l>Tormenta, carcer, vngulae,</l>
                  <l>Stridenſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> flammis lamina,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rudent: periſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>han. de Vince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</note>At<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ipſa poenarum vltima</l>
                  <l>Mors, Chriſtianis ludus eſt</l>
               </q> Tormentes, and priſon, and torturing cooles, and burning plates of mettall, and death it ſelfe, the laſt puniſhment of all; theſe are but a ſporte and paſtime to thoſe that beleeue in Chriſt. What cauſed them ſo patientlye to endure theſe tribulations and fyrie tryalls, but the full aſſurance of the inualuable treaſure of heauen? For then ſhall the righteous ſtand in greate boldneſſe, before the face of ſuch as haue tormented them; and ſhall receiue a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous kingdome, and a beawtifull crown of the Lords hand; but the vngodly ſhall bee ſcattered and ouerthrowne with thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts, and lightnings, and floods.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 5, 1, 16, 21,</note>Out of all this it appereth, that the ſoules
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6972:31"/> of the faithfull after death are in eternall ioye and felicity. Neither is there any mean place to ſtay them in, for their ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, as ſome dreame: or for their purging as ſome fantaſie: but as the ſoule of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> was preſently carried by the Angells into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, aſſoone as it was vnfettered out of the bandes of the fleſh:<note place="margin">Luke, 16.22.</note> and as the ſoule of the theefe was with Chriſt in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> within fower howres after he deſired to be remembred of Chriſt: ſo our Sauiour ſayth generally of all the faithfull, that hee that heareth his worde,<note place="margin">Luke 23, 43.</note> and beleeueth him that ſent him, hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euerlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation,<note place="margin">Ioh: 5, 24.</note> but hath paſſed from death to life? And that we might the ſooner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that there is no <hi>interim</hi> and ſpace between y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of the body &amp; the eternal life and ioy of the ſoule, hee confirmes his ſpeach with a double affirmation, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oath, ſaying, <hi>verily,</hi> and <hi>verily,</hi> I ſay it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſo.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu. 14, 13,</hi> a parti: in poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: &amp; vt vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gata tranſlatio, amodo; i. ſtatim</note> Alſo the voice taught <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine,</hi> that whoſoeuer dye in the Lord, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the faith of Chriſt, they are bleſſed, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt from their labours, and receiue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eward of their workes, and when? <hi>Heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fter,</hi> preſently &amp; immediatly after they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6972:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> are called out of this mortall life. This ſtops the beaſtly and blaſphemous mouth of the <hi>Sadduces,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts 23, 8</note> and fully puts them to ſilence; who affirmed, that there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, nor <hi>Angell,</hi> nor ſpirit: and of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picurus</hi> the belligod Philoſopher, <hi>who was a moſt deteſtable defender of pleaſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>actant. diuin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtit. <hi>l. 3,</hi> c. <hi>17</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and thought that Man was onely borne to enioy pleaſure, and ſayd that the Soule dyeth after the death of the body:</hi> and of <hi>Plinie,</hi> who was not aſhamed to write,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mnibus à ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em a die, eade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uae ante primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ec magis à <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orte ſenſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llus, aut corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, aut animae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>àm ante na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lem. Plin. lib, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cap, <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that it fares with all men after the laſt day, as it did before the firſt day: and that there is no more ſenſe and feeling, eyther of body, or minde, after we are dead, then there was before we were borne:</hi> and of <hi>Lucretius</hi> a far ſwine of <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures</hi> ſtie, who impudently opens his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane mouth againſt heauen, and ſayes,
<q>
                  <l>Quod ſi immortalis noſtra foret mens,</l>
                  <l>Non tam ſe moriens diſſolui conquereretur,</l>
                  <l>Sed magis ire foras, neſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> relinquere vt a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gnis Gauder et:</l>
               </q> If our ſoule did liue for euer (ſaith he) ſhee would not in death complaine of hir diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; but rather ſhe would reioyce to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of the fleſh, and would be glad to leaue the garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the body, as the ſnake
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6972:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> is ioyfull for the vncaſing from his oulde ſkin. But <hi>Lactantius</hi> dooth moſt acutelie and learnedly confute him, ſaying; <hi>how can it be known that any doth vnderſtand that he is diſſolued, or els ſet at liberty, ſens the tung is dumbe when a man dyeth? For while he vnderſtands, and can ſpeake, hee is not yet diſſolued: when he is diſſolued: hee can neither vnderſtand, nor ſpeake. So that complaine of his diſſolution, either yet he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, or now he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not.</hi> But (ſaith) <hi>Lucretius before he be diſſolued he perceiues that he ſhal be diſſolued. What ſhold <hi>I</hi> ſay: that we ſee many in death not to complaine of their diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (as Lucretius ſaieth] but to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, that they do goe and departe &amp; walke out of the body, and either declaring this by geſture, or vttering it by wordes; if they can ſpeake ſo long? By which it is euident that there is no diſſolution, but a ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which declars the remayning of the ſoul after death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lactant, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, instit, l, <hi>7, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 12.</hi>
               </note> For as a candle while it is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lanterne, it enlightens the lantern, &amp; if it bee taken out, although the lanterne bee lefte darke, yet the candle ſhines more cleerly then it did before: ſo while the ſoul is in the body it is the light and gouernor
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6972:33"/> thereof, and when it forſakes the body, although the body be left dead and inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, yet then the ſoule enioyes her proper vigor and brightneſſe. Damnable are all the aſſertions, that maintaine the morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the ſoule: for if ſhee did periſhe with the body, and had no ſenſe &amp; feeling after death: how can the godly after death bee in Gods preſence, and ſerue him day and night in his temple, and haue God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling among them, &amp; bee fedd, &amp; gouerned, &amp; ledd to the liuely fountains of waters, and haue all teares wiped from their eyes? as the Angell here affirmeth. Cleere is that ſpeeche of <hi>Moſes</hi> for the eternitye of the ſoule, when hee ſayes, that <hi>the Lorde god made the man of the duſt of the grounde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. 2.7</note> 
               <hi>&amp; breathed in his face breath of life.</hi> In which words the man of god puteth a plaine dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the foule of man, and the ſoule that is in other creatures: for the ſoule (or life) of beaſts proceeded from the ſame ſubſtance and matter whereof their bodies were made: but the ſoule of man is a ſpirituall and diuine thing, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it proceeded from god, muſt needes remaine for euer. Manifeſt is the ſaying of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6972:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> God to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the burning buſhe: <hi>I am the God of Abraham, the god of Iſaac and the god of Iaacob.</hi> He ſayth,<note place="margin">Exod, 3, 6,</note> I am not I was: to ſhew that hee is continually their God: and as this prooues the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the body againſt the Saduces (For if <hi>Abraham, Izhak:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt, 22, 32:</hi> Quomod foeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſi ex parte perituri, Tertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de resurrec: carnis.</note> 
               <hi>and Iaacob</hi> bee gods; they are altogether his, and they cannot be throughlie bleſſed if one parte of them ſhould periſh &amp; decay, ſo it fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the immortality of the Soule after death For if the faithfull are alway gods people, and god is alwaye their God, and Lorde, they muſt needs liue in ſoule, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen before the general reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for <hi>god is not the god of the dead but of the liuinge.</hi> Euident is the eternity of the Soule out of that of patient <hi>Iob;</hi> who in his extream affliction, expreſſed notwithſtanding his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of immortality, <hi>thogh god ſlay me</hi> (ſayth he) with death of body, <hi>yet will I truſt in him,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhall inherit the light of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting glorie. And he confidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth his beleef touching life euerlaſting &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying,<note place="margin">Iob, 13, 15,</note> 
               <hi>I am ſure my redee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer liueth, &amp; thogh after my ſkin worms de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this body, yet ſhall J ſe god in my fleſh whome
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6972:34"/> 
                  <hi>I</hi> my ſelf ſhal ſee, and mine eies ſhal behold and none other for me, though my vaynes are nowe conſumed within mee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 19.25,</note> Which wordes of his bicauſe of theire infallible crueth and certaintie; he wiſheth that all men mighte knowe:, And that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they mighte be written,<note place="margin">Iob, 19, 23,</note> yea written euen in a booke, and grauen with an y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron penne in leade, or in ſtone for euer. When <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaies to God, <hi>thou wilte not leaue my ſoule in graue, neyther wilte thou ſuffer thine holy on to ſee corruption: thou wilt ſhew me the path of life:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal, 16, 10.11</note> 
               <hi>in thy preſence is the fulneſſe of ioye, and at thy righte hand there are pleaſures for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more:</hi> Hee declares two benefites, of which both himſelfe, and all the Godlye ſhould be made partakers through chriſt: to witte the reſurrection of the fleſh; and that moſte ioyfull, moſte pleaſaunt and eternall life. And though the vngodlye ar incloſed in their own fat, &amp; ſpeak proud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their mouthes, &amp; think but of their portion in this life: hauing their bellies filled with hid treaſure: &amp; leauing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of their ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for their children, yet he is vndoubtedly perſwaded, that after hee
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6972:34"/> was deliuered out of the greate and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite troubles of this worlde, hee ſhoulde beholde in heauen the comfortable face &amp; countenance of god according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; and ſhould perfectly bee vnited vnto God, and ſee him as he is.<note place="margin">Pſal: 17.10, 14</note> What plainer then that of <hi>Salomon;</hi> who ſayes, that when man dyeth, <hi>duſt returneth to the earth, as it was, and the ſpirite then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth to god that gaue it?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles 12.7:</note> As though the royall Preacher ſhould ſay, although the body and ſoule ar conioyned &amp; coupled together, yet they are of diſlike nature: for the bodie is groſſe, and may be ſeene &amp; handled, and the body is made of the earth a ponderous and corruptible eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and is as it were the veſſell that containes the ſoule: but the ſoule is ſubtile, and not to be ſeene, or handled, and the ſoule hath no earthy mixture in it: but beeing endewed with ſuch ſkill, ſuch force, and ſuch nimbleneſſe, ſhee muſt needes haue her beginning from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and although they are ſo neeerely conioyned in this world, that the deſtruction of the on, may ſeeme to be the diſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pation of the other; yet when death makes a diuorce &amp; ſepara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6972:35"/> betweene them,<note place="margin">Lucretius ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itus quid aſſere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quod dog <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ma defendere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os verſus poſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it: Cedit item <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etro de terra quod fuit ante <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n terras &amp; quod miſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ex atheris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ris Id rursum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oeli rellatum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>templa, recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. Lact, diu, inst, lib, <hi>7,</hi> cap, <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> then eyther of them retourne into their owne nature: the body which was of the earth is reſolued into earth, and that which was from the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſpirite, alway endureth and flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, becaus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of God is euerlaſting The truth wherof is ſo powerful, it cauſed the foreſayde <hi>Epicurean Lucretius,</hi> euen in deſpight of his helliſh Prophaneneſſe, to confeſſe it. What plainer to confirme the eternall life of the ſoule, then where <hi>Iſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> bringes in other potentates that were dead before deriding the inſolency of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that though hee ſayed in harte, that hee woulde aſcend into heauen and exhalt his throne aboue the ſtarres of God, and aſcend aboue the height of the clouds and bee like the moſte high, yet he was become weak by death aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as they: and his pompe and the ſounde of the violes was broughte downe to the graue and the worme was ſpreadd vnder him, and the wormes did couer him?<note place="margin">Iſai, 14, 9.</note> For hee woulde not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute this ſcorninge to the deade, if ther were the ſame ende both to man &amp; beaſt. What plainer for to ſtop the mouths of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6972:35"/> 
               <hi>Atheiſts</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contradict y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> immortality of the ſoul then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaying of Chriſt our Lord in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel: <hi>Fear you not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> (ſaith be) <hi>which kill the body: but ar not able to kil the ſoul but rather feare him, which is able to deſtroy both ſoule &amp; body in Hell</hi> If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoul ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſlain,<note place="margin">Mat, 10, 28,</note> and if it may bee puniſhed in hell after this life, it is euerlaſting, &amp; can neuer dy. And therfore excellently ſpake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> that ſayed thus to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tormenter, thou blody tyrant thou art deceiued if thou ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe to deſtroy me, by renting my body which is ſubiect to deth:<note place="margin">Erras cruente, meam, Te rer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poenam ſume re, quum mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra morti ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxia Dilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinata interficis? Eſt alter hic intri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> violare quem nullus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt, Liber, qui etus integer, Expers doloru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> triſtium. Prudent periſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> phan de vince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio. <hi>Gen; 5, 24,</hi>
               </note> ther is on within thou canſt not wrong; which is free, quiet intire, and not to be payned with torturs this body which thou endeuoureſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy with ſuch force and furie, is but a brittle, and earthen veſſell which maye be eaſily broken into ſhiuers; but aſſaye now, to cut and puniſh him that is within, and that regardes not thy rage, prouoke him, and ſearch him, thou ſhalte find him inuincible; vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>querable, an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derling to no calamities; and ſubiected to God alone? Could <hi>Enoch</hi> walk w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god after this life: if ſoul &amp; body dye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> together Could <hi>Saul</hi> deſire the <hi>Pithones</hi> to raiſe vp
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6972:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> the prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> vnto him,<note place="margin">1, Sam. 28, 11,</note> if the ſoule and body dyed together? Coulde <hi>Dauid</hi> mourn ſo bitterly for his rebellious ſoun <hi>Abſolom,</hi> when hee cryed out; <hi>O my ſonn Abſolom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam, 18, 33,</note> 
               <hi>my ſonne, my ſonne Abſolom, woulde God I had dyed for thee, <hi>O</hi> Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom, my ſonne, my ſonne.</hi> Would he haue ſo bitterly lamented his death, if the ſoule and body dyed together? For <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith.<note place="margin">De doctrina Chriſti.</note> 
               <hi>Non orbitatem filii doluit Dauid, dum luget Abſolonem filium, ſed quia nouerat in quas poenas tam impie adul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tera et parricidalis anima raperetur.</hi> Dauid was not ſo much greeued for the death &amp; loſſe of a ſonne when hee bewailed his ſonne <hi>Abſolom,</hi> but it was for that hee knew how greuouſly that ſoule was pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed after death, which in this life was giuen to ſuch impiety, adultery, &amp; hai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nous murther. Could, <hi>Elias, &amp; El zeus, and Chriſt</hi> and the Apoſtles raize vp the dead;<note place="margin">1 Kings, 17, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, Kings, 4, &amp;, 13, Mat. 9 Luk. 9 Iohn. 11, Act. 9. &amp; 20, Acts. 7.59.</note> if the ſoule and bodie died together? Could Stephe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay at his ſtoning to death <hi>Lord Ieſus receiue my ſpirite,</hi> If the foule &amp; body died together? Coulde <hi>Paule</hi> raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with a deſire to come to the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6972:36"/> of felicity and therefore abhorring this wretched and calamitous life, crie out earneſtly and ſaie: <hi>O wretched man that <hi>I</hi> am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom, 7, 24.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall deliuer mee from this body of death;</hi> if the ſoule &amp; body died to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether? But why labour I ſo much amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Chriſtians to prooue the eternity of the ſoule? who doe firmely aſſent to the <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Creed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhews vs life eternal: ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially ſince the moſt ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; profound <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſophers</hi> amongſt the Ethnicks, haue in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery age with one mouth, and one minde ſubſcribed thereunto? Of which let one <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeake for them all,<note place="margin">Sen, lib, <hi>10,</hi> ſuaſoriar.</note> 
               <hi>nothing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes but our bodye, which becauſe of the weake frailty thereof, it is obnoxious to death, ſubiect to chaunces, expoſed to proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criptions. But the ſoule whoſe beginning is diuine, is harmed neyther by old age, nor death and when ſhee is looſed from her burthenſome bands ſhee ſpeedily repaires to her proper place, and to the ſtarres that ar of the ſame nature.</hi> It were ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full therfore for Chriſtians, not to houlde faſt the bleſſed hope of immortality, &amp; not to cleaue thereunto as to a ſure anchor, ſince heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men haue ſo euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly taught
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6972:37"/> the eternity of the ſoule, by groping after it in the darkeneſſe of errour, onelye by the direction of the naturall lighte and infallible principles remaining in mans minde after <hi>Adams</hi> fall; and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſince the godly and faithfull are at no reſt in this mortall life,<note place="margin">1 Cor, 15, 19,</note> 
               <hi>if in this life onelie they had hope in chriſt, they were of all men the moſte miſerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, dooth Sathan, and the fleſh, and the worlde allure vs, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe our ſhoulders from bearing the ſweete and eaſie yoake of Chriſt, and our feete from walking in the path of Gods lawes; and to enioye in this worlde the pleaſures of iniquitie for a time? the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſcripture dooth plentifully teache vs, that our ſoules liue for euer; the godlie in heauen; the vngodly in torment: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how readie ought wee to bee, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vngodlineſſe, and worldlie luſtes; and to liue ſoberlie, and righteouſly, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in this preſent world: knowing this, that one day wee ſhall bee called to an account, how we haue imployed our ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents and ſtewardſhip. Doth the careleſſe Chriſtian perſwade vs, to runne with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6972:37"/> him in the ſame exceſſe of ryot, of dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, of carnall ſecurity, of ſwearing, of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continency, of hypocriſie, of malice, of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, of forgetting of God, of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte of his worde, and deſpiſing his kindnes &amp; long ſuffering, not perceiuing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his bountifulnes leads vs to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance? Let vs anſwere y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſeek eternall life &amp; not eternal death, &amp; that we wil flee ſin, and liue in the awe and worſhippe ef God, becauſe the end of the vngodly is to be deſtroyed and rooted out at the laſt but godlineſſe hath the promiſe of the life pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> and of that is to come. And howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſome wallow in their ſenſuality, and freeze in the dregs of prophaneneſſe, yet let vs that are a choſen generation, and a royall prieſthoode, and an holy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a peculiar people, ſhewe forth the vertues of him that hath called vs out of darkeneſſe into his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous lighte, and as ſtraungers and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes, let vs abſtaine from fleſhly luſts, that fighte againſte the ſpirite, and let vs haue our conuerſation honeſt among all men, that by our good works which they ſhall ſee, they maye glorifie God in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6972:38"/> the day of viſitation.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et, 2, 9 &amp;c.</note> Dooth ſickneſſe, or ſorow, or pouerty, or flaunders, or daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, or any affliction or tribulation pres vs; ſo as being therewith ſurcharged, we are likely to ſinke, and be diſmayed? Let vs encourage our ſelues with the contem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plation and meditation of heauenly ioies; and let vs be ſtedfaſt, vnmoueable, aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dante alwaies in the worke of the Lorde, foraſmuch as wee know, that our laboure is not in vaine in the Lorde. When terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ghaſtly death woulde diſcourage vs: let vs remember that death is ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp into victory through the death of Chriſt and therefore we may confidently ſay,<note place="margin">Cor. 15.54</note> 
               <hi>ô death where is thy ſting, ô graue where is thy victorye?</hi> and that death is made vnto vs a doore into eternall glory, and that when we depart hence, our ſouls ſhall paſſe into heauen, as into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon city and dwelling place of all belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers; becauſe wee are no more ſtraungers and forreiners, but citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with the ſaints aod of the houſhold of god, and are builte vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles and prophets, Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe being the cheefe corner ſtone. For wee knowe, that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6972:38"/> if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle be deſtroyed, wee haue a building of God,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.19, 2</note> that is, an houſe not made with handes, but eternall in the heauens.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.1.</note> Our depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hence is a going out of priſon, and an entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce into life that knows no death. Our fathers are all gone before, and all their offſpring ſhall followe. What run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner when hee hath begonne his race, doth not houlde on cheerefullie till hee attayn to the goale? What Marriner in the darke night and tempeſtuous ſeas, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to reſt in the quiet harborough? What pilgrime wandering in a ſtraunge coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, longs not to come to his owne dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, wife, friendes, and children? And ſhall wee bee ſo loathe to goe to heauen, and <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> the houſe of Saintes: to GOD our Father, Chriſte our redeemer and Brother; the holy Ghoſte our comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? As the ſparkle of fire ſtill mountes vpwarde, and the water fleetes downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and euery thinge goes to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and naturall place of ſtaye; ſo our ſoules which came from heauen, muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoure and ſtriue to goe to the Father of lights; whome to behoulde is life, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6972:39"/> not to ſee is death. We trauell through colde and heate, daunger and labour, hills and vallies, ſeas and lands for earthly and periſhing ritches: and ſhould a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand deathes ſtop vs, to ſee ſo many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, prophets, patriarches, martyrs, and Saints in <hi>Paradiſe? Cyprian</hi> ſayth, <hi>Eius eſt mortem timere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e mortalit.</note> 
               <hi>qui ad Chriſtum nolit ire: eius eſt ad chriſtum nolle ire, qui ſe non credit cum Chriſto incipere regnare. It is for him to feare death, who woulde not goe to Chriſt: it is for him to bee vnwilling to goe to chriſt, who beleeues not, that after death hee ſhall beginne to raigne with chriſt.</hi> When our friends are taken from vs by death: let vs not thinke that they are loſt, and vtterly periſhed; but that they are gone before vs into the place and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of reſt: and therefore let vs not mourne, as they doe which are voyde of the hope of the reſurrection and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life: for as wee beleeue that Ieſus is dead, and riſen, euen ſo they which ſleepe in Ieſus are liuing in ioy, and god will bring them againe at the laſt daye with Ieſus: and let vs comfort our ſelues one another with theſe wordes. When
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6972:39"/> wee ſee the godlye in this worlde,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.14 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as it were forſaken now and then, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible to the eyes of men; but the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times ſprowting as the green Bay tree: let this ſupporte and proppe vs vp, that one day <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, and <hi>Diues</hi> tormented. When wee conſider the inconſtancie of worldlie ritches, and honour, and fauoure, and promotion, and friendſhippe in this life: let vs learne hereby, not to loue the world, neither the thinges that are in the world; for the luſte of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, the pride of life, and all that is in this worlde, paſſeth away; but hee that fulfilleth the will of God,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.15 16.17.</note> abideth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: and let vs ſolace our ſelues, with the ſtable, permanent, and vnchaungeable ioyes of heauen: for the ſtate of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and vngodly after death cannot bee chaunged; there is a greate gulfe ſette betweene heauen and hell,<note place="margin">Luke 16, 26.</note> ſo that they that woulde goe from bliſſe to puniſhmente, cannot; neither can any come from tormente to bliſſe. Finallie, when wee are ſoliciced, eyther by the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6972:40"/> ſuggeſtion of Sathan, or the allurements of pleaſure, or the perſwaſion of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtes, or the weakeneſſe of the fleſh, to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that there is no life after death, and that the ſoule vaniſheth awaye into nothing, when a man dyeth: let vs call to minde, that heauen and earth ſhall ſooner paſſe, then the worde of the Lorde ſhal fall to the grounde; which teacheth, that after bodylie death, the ſouls of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and righteous are in the handes of the Lorde, and enioye eternall comforte: and (if wee cannot remember all that hath beene now deliuered,) let vs alway carrie the ſumme and quinteſſence of this one place of Scripture imprinted and ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen firmelie in our heartes, in which the Angell declares vnto bleſſed <hi>John,</hi> that all faithfull ſoules, that in this life haue waſhed their long robes, and made them white in the bloud of the Lamb, and haue onelie relyed on the merites, death, and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt; they are after this life in the preſence of the throne of God; and ſerue him continuallye in the temple of heauen; and dwell eternally with God, &amp; God with them: they hunger, and thirſte
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6972:40"/> no more: they are moleſted and accum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with the heate of the Sunn no more, and afflicted with tribulation no more: for Ieſus Chriſt the Lambe of God, which is in the middeſt of the Throne ſhall feede them, and rule them, &amp; leade them to the liuelie fountaines of waters, and GOD ſhall wipe awaye all teares from theyr eyes.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the interpretation and explication of this text of holy Scripture. And although I haue already very much exceeded my vſuall manner,<note place="margin">The chriſtia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> life and god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> death of the Lady Court <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney.</note> in that I haue ſo long and largely inſiſted on the thinges propoſed, and thereby tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (perhappes) may beginne to creepe vpon you; yet I muſt a little longer pray your attention, while I breeflye ſpeake ſome thinge of the life and death of this right worſhipful and deuoute gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which is now to be buried; and which hath occaſioned me at this time to vnfold vnto you this portion of Gods word. The virtues and graces wherewith ſhee was adorned, as they merited greate commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; ſo I am ſorrie that they may not now be blazed, by the eloquence of <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:6972:41"/> or the tongue of Angells.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al. Max. l, <hi>8, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</hi>
               </note> For as <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the greate forbade anye to painte him but <hi>Apelles,</hi> and to carue him but <hi>Lyſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> leaſte his excellencie ſhoulde bee aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by vnnoble Artificers: ſo the woorthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this religious Ladie deſeruedlie craues, to bee deſcribed of ſome one endued with ſingular guifte of ſpeaking, who mighte counteruaile her worthie workes with aunſwerable wordes. Howſoeuer it bee, this comfortes mee, that I ſpeake not before ſtraungers vnacquainted with her godlie qualities, that therefore woulde aſke a more copious declaration of the thinges they knowe not but before thoſe, who hauing had very long experience and triall of her godlineſſe, eyther wil ſupplie the defecte of the Speaker through theyr own manifould knowledge; or els by one worde wil coniecture what the whole ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence meanes.</p>
            <p>And for that the life of a true Chriſtian conſiſteth in beleeuing and liuing; I wil beginne firſte with the ſinceritie of her faith. She was not like many lukewarm <hi>Politicians,</hi> that either are <hi>Atheiſtes,</hi> of no religion at al; or els <hi>Chameleon</hi>-like turne
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6972:41"/> with the time and iump with opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but ſhee embraced the ancient and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike fayth, cleauinge to the ſound doctrine deliuered in the word of God and abhorring the ſuperſtitious cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of mens deuiſes.</p>
            <p>This fayth was not hypocriticall, but true: not temporarie but permanent, not idle, but working not deade but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, &amp; ſpringing foorth with the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all good workes, euen as a good tree brings foorth good fruite; and a wholeſome well yeeldes out whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome water. Her earneſt loue of Gods word &amp; great meaſure of knowledge of Chriſts goſpell, of which ſhe hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes been an affectionate, hearer, and a diligent performer, ſufficiently declare what theſe workes of fayth were. For ſhe was not onely painefull in reſorting to the Church, to pray w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregation &amp; to heare the word of God, as long as ſtrength of bodie permitted, but euen ſince age &amp; weakenes debarred her of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſtome, ſhe hath ordinarily &amp; dayly cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed prayers to be vſed, &amp; the ſcriptures &amp;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6972:42"/> pure expoſitors of them to bee reade at home; making the worde of God a <hi>Ianc</hi>-horne to directe her feete, and Manna to ſuſtayne her ſoule; ſo paſſing her time (for many yeares) that her life might be deemed a meditation of death, and a preparation for entrance into the life to come.</p>
            <p>What ſhoulde I ſpeake of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian gouerning of her houſehoulde; and of her eſpeciall care, that thoſe which were about her might bee taughte the lawes of the Lorde, to walke as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the profeſſors of the goſpell? What ſhoulde I ſpeake of her patience, that beeing in ſundry wiſe toſſed and tryed with the croſſes of this life, yet (like a rocke beaten on by the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling floods) ſhee ſtoode conſtant; ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring thankes to God, aſwell for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, as for proſperity; and taking euery affliction in good parte, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the loue of GOD to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes her? This patience was ſhaken by the captiuitie of her huſband, an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and woorthie gentleman;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6972:42"/> who beeing <hi>Sheriffe</hi> of this county was taken priſoner, and in extreame perill to bee cruellie handled by the rebells in the Weſtern Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motion, in the raigne of king <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>6.:</hi> again, by the death of her foreſaid huſband, within few yeers after; again by the change of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into forged ſuperſtition in the dayes of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">During all which time, ſhe had the form of praier vſed in her houſe, which was authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the dayes of king Edward the 6.</note> which pinched her with exceeding grief; againe by the death of al her ſons, gentlemen of great hope, again by the death of al her ſons in law, men of worſhipful regard; again by the death of ſom of her nephews, &amp; daughters, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women liuely treading in the virtuous ſteps of their godly mother; &amp; againe by the death of ſome of her neeces; this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience (I ſay) was ſhaken, but it ſtoode firmely; as an Oake that is ſurely roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted weighes not the blaſtes of winde. What ſhoulde I ſpeake of her humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and lowlineſſe of minde; which bewrayed it ſelfe in all her outwarde actions, and in her verie apparrell; in that a Gentlewoman of her degree and ranke, woulde ſo plainelie attire
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6972:43"/> her ſelfe; obſeruing the rule of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> who warneth women not to goe gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſlie in their apparrell, by brayding the hayre, and trimming aboute with golde, but to bee cloathed with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious garmente of the inwarde man. This humility was great,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 3.3.4</note> bothe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes God, and man: towards God, in that abounding with good workes which proceeded from a ſauing fayth, yet ſhee loathed to bee commended for the ſame, confeſſing that it was nothing ſhee did: and that it was ſo farre off, that ſhee truſted to bee ſaued by her own merites, as that ſhee renounced them, and placed them among her euil deeds in that reſpecte; and wholly relyed, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie depended, whollie reſted vpon Chriſt Ieſus, her onelye redeemer, mediatour, aduocate, and Sauioure. And to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes man this humility was appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante; in that ſhee diſdained not the meaneſt, but with affabilitie applyed her ſelfe to thoſe that were of the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſorte; and in that not onely in her life, ſhee declined from pompe and vayn
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6972:43"/> ſhewes, but alſo ſtraightly and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times charged, that her funerals ſhould be ſolemnized without any ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pompe. But what ſhoulde I ſpeak of her promptneſſe to aſſiſte both riche and poor with her counſell and aduiſe? for ſhee was endued with greate wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, rare memory, graue iudgemente, and ſharpe foreſighte. What ſhoulde I ſpeake of her temperance &amp; ſobriety of her loue and liberality to ſchollars? kindneſſe to miniſters of the worde of God? and entertainement of all good people, of her conſtancy in her widdow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heade? For of fower ſcore and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeeres, (or very neere thereaboutes) of her age, ſhee ſpente fiftye &amp; fiue in the time of widdowehead of her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaungeable and ſtedfaſt zeale in the truth of Chriſte Ieſus. So that if <hi>Iohn</hi> the elder had liued in this age, he might haue ſaluted her by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of <hi>Elect La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> &amp; might haue reioyced,<note place="margin">2, Ioh: 4.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d her &amp; her childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; her of ſpring walking in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth. Al theſe things (for that they are ſo well knowne) I ſleightly poynte at
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6972:44"/> with the forefinger, leauing them to your ſecret conſiderations.</p>
            <p>As for her remorſe, compaſſion, and liberality towards the poore and needy members of Chriſt bodie, not one prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher in tenne howers, nor tenne prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in one hower are able to expreſſe it as it doth deſerue. The <hi>Orphanes</hi> &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe children, that ſhe hath nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, the deſolate widowes that ſhee hath ſuſtayned, the afflicted ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that ſhee hath releeued; the ſick, impotente and, maymed Souldiers that ſhee hath refreſhed: the diſeaſed perſons with ſore eies, and manifolde hurtes, and diuers infirmities, that ſhee hath eaſed, applying the ſalu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> waters and medicines with her owne hands, gyue plentifull teſtimony with full mouth of her exceeding charitye. What weeke, nay what daye, nay almoſte what howre paſſed ouer, where in ſome poore, or other did not taſte of her bountifulneſſe?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uke, 19, 8,</note> Shee excelled <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus;</hi> who ſtood foorth, and ſaid <hi>behold
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6972:44"/> Lord the halfe of my goods <hi>I</hi> giue to the poore.</hi> Shee was not inferior to <hi>Iob,</hi> who turned not his eie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore,<note place="margin">Iob, 31, 16, 17,</note> but cloathed the naked with his garment fed the hungry with his meate, and lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the pilgrime in his houſe. Shee is to be linked in prayſe with <hi>Dorcas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 9.39.</note> for if <hi>Peeter</hi> were heer and ſhee were (as <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cas</hi>) to be raiſed againe; howe infinite is the number of coates and garmentes that the poore would ſhewe foorth, or ſpeake of, which they haue receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her liberality? She is not to be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the holy and charitable we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Luke. 8, 2,</note> men which miniſtred to our Sauiour himſelfe on earth, for as they did mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to the head, ſo did ſhe to the body and therefore Chriſte accountes that meat, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> drinck, that cloathing,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.36.</note> that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainemente, and that viſitinge and comforte which is imployed on the ſillie poore, to bee beſtowed on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. And as the Iewes when that they deſired Chriſte to helpe the <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rions</hi> ſeruaunte, they ſaide,<note place="margin">Luke, 7, 4, 5.</note> that hee was worthye for whome our Sauiour
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6972:45"/> Sauioure ſhoulde doe it. <hi>For hee loues our nation</hi> (ſay they) <hi>he hath built vs a ſinagogue:</hi> ſoe if odious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude poſſeſſe not the harts of the poore, whome in manifolde ſorte this compaſſionate and charitable Lady hath releeued, they will with one voyce crie out and ſaye, that ſhee was moſte worthye of longer life and of doubled dayes, becauſe ſhee was a nurſe to the needy an eie to the blinde, a foote to the lame, a mother to the <hi>Orphanes,</hi> a ſtaffe to the afflicted, a comforter and ſupporter to the diſtreſſed and miſerable. I perceiue I am en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the broade <hi>Ocean</hi> with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaied ſayles, and therefore leaſt I be caried further then I maye quickly returne, I will haſten to draw towards the ſhore.</p>
            <p>Her life being beawtified with theſe induements and qualityes, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſpent her daies in grace &amp; godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, who maye doubt: but that her death and diſſolution was correſpondent to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6972:45"/> her former race? At ſundrie times when ſhe was viſited with ſickneſſe, ſhee was not deſirous of longer life, neither woulde ſhee haue others to put her in hope of recouery: but wholy longing to be remooued hence, and to dwell with God the Lorde; firſte making a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie and Chriſtian co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of her fayth, in God the Father, the ſonne and the holy Ghoſt, ſhe ſtill deſired with Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon to departe in peace, with Paul to be diſſolued &amp; to be with Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.29.</note> accoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting chriſt to be her adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage both in life and death,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.21: Rom. 14.8 Pſal, 84, 10.</note> and her ſelfe to bee the Lordes whither ſhee liued or died, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Dauid wiſhing to in habite moſt amiable inhabitations of heuen, &amp; eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it better to remaine one daye, in the houſe of God, then a thouſand in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of this vile world. And thus beeing of a good age, ful of daies fuller of good works, hauing made her, robe white in the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bs blud, &amp; a long time being prepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red for her departure; when infirmity &amp; laſt ſicknes attainted her alway ſetling &amp; fixing her confidence in chriſt, praying deuoutly
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6972:46"/> to God, who hath promiſed to heare the petitions of them that faithfully call vpon him; alwaye committing her ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, into the hands of her creator, redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and comforter, at laſt her ſanctified and refined ſoul leauing the corruptible bodie departed out of tribulation and this valley of miſerie into the boſome of faithefull Abraham.<note place="margin">Reu. 14, 13. and. 7, 9</note> For why ſhould I not ſo ſay? ſens they are bleſſed, that dye in the Lorde, and they reſte from their laboures:<note place="margin">and, 2.10. and 4.4. and, 22, 1, 2. and. 7:16, 17</note> they are cloathed with the long white robe of innocency, they are adorned with the incorruptible crowne of glorye, that neuer withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth:<note place="margin">and 21.11</note> they eate of the fruite of the tree of life, and drinke of the water of life, they hunger and thirſt no more they haue all teares and remembrance of euils wiped from them:<note place="margin">Heb: 12 22,</note> they are Citizens of the celeſtiall and new Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, whoſe walls are pure goulde and the gates pearles, and whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitantes are the <hi>Patriarkes,</hi> and holye Prophets, Apoſtles, Arke an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, Angels and Saintes of all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6972:46"/> One that wrote of the life <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> once Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> ſayes of him.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nec dubito, qui ſit vixit,<note place="margin">Chriſtoph, Io<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in car de vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta wiccami winton Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi.</note> ſic mortuus idem eſt</l>
               <l>Quin ſit apud ſuperos nobilis vmbra Deos:</l>
               <l>Cur dubite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? nam ſi coeleſtis clauditur Aula,</l>
               <l>Heroi tanto, cui precor, illa patet?</l>
            </q>
            <p>I doubt not, (ſaith hee) but hee that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo, and died ſo, is among the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpirits of heauen, why ſhold I doubt, For if the pallace of heauen be ſhutte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſo worthy a man, to whome doeth it ſtande open? May not I without flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery chaunge the gender, and ſaye of this religious and good Lady? I doubt not but that ſhe that liued and died ſo, is nowe among the bleſſed ſoules in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen: why ſhould I doubte? for if the gate of heauen be ſhut to ſo worthy a woman to whome ſhall it be opened?</p>
            <p>And as a certaine yll <hi>Oratour</hi> that thought hee had mooued his auditors to compaſſion in his epilogue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: when he was ſitten downe, and had aſked of <hi>Catulus,</hi> whether hee thought hee had mooued them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6972:47"/> or not;<note place="margin">Cic. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Oratore.</note> 
               <hi>Catulus</hi> anſwered, <hi>nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eſſe puto tam durum, cui non oratio tua miſeranda viſa ſit;</hi> I thinke none ſo hard of heart, as that hee pitties not thy ſlender and ſimple ſpeeche; So I thinke that all that haue hearde mee ſpeake of this right worſhipfull gentlewoman, ſo ſlenderly and ſimplie, are mooued to compaſſion and pitty; becauſe my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is ſo infinitely exceeded by her me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morable deeds, and that they will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare me to a rude and vnſkilfull painter that hath pourtraied thoſe things courſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and groſely, which ſhoulde haue beene painted with fair and freſh colours. But I hope, that my willingnes ſhall make ſatiſfaction for my want; and that this common oyle, which I haue powred out of my vnpoliſhed Alablaſter box, to honor her buriall with all, ſhall be accepted in ſteed of pretious ſpikenard.</p>
            <p>This onely remaineth; that the poorer ſort deſire god, to encreaſe the number of thoſe, that may be like to this vertuous Lady; and that the wealthier ſort labour after her exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, to deſerue ſo well of the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6972:47"/> needy, that their departure may bee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and their memory bleſſed; and that both ritch and poore imitate her in faith, zeale, patience, humility, vnfained charity, and the reſidue of her rare and notable virtues: to the glorifiing of Gods name, to the edifiyng of the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to our attainement of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſaluation, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: to whom with the father, &amp; the holy ghoſt, be giuen all honor, praiſe, and glorie, now and euermore: Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
